<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-model href="../segMarkerTester.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:pitt="https://github.com/ebeshero/Pittsburgh_Frankenstein" xmlns:mith="http://mith.umd.edu/sc/ns1#" xmlns:th="http://www.blackmesatech.com/2017/nss/trojan-horse" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Bridge Phase 5: Witness f1818, Collation unit C06</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Frankenstein Variorum Project</authority>
            <date>2018</date>
            <availability>
               <licence>Distributed under a Creative Commons
                                  Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License</licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Produced from collation output prepared in batch file processing on  2018-10-03 19:23:51.102012 .</p>
            <p>Edited to correct alignments and prepared for the Frankenstein Variorum spine on  2020-01-02T22:33:56.362-05:00.</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="collation">
            <seg part="I" xml:id="C06a_app1-f1818__I">
            <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_div4_p25">August 13th, 17—.</p>
            </seg>
            <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_div4_p26">
               <seg part="F" xml:id="C06a_app1-f1818__F">My affection for my guest increases every day. He excites at once my admiration and my pity to an astonishing degree. How can I see so noble a creature destroyed by </seg>
               <seg xml:id="C06a_app2-f1818">misery </seg>
               <seg xml:id="C06a_app3-f1818">without feeling the most poignant grief? He is so gentle, yet so wise; his mind is so cultivated; </seg>
               <seg xml:id="C06a_app4-f1818">and when he speaks, </seg>
               <seg part="I" xml:id="C06a_app5-f1818__I">although his words are culled with the choicest art, yet they flow with rapidity and unparalleled eloquence.</seg>
            </p>
            <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_div4_p27">
               <seg part="F" xml:id="C06a_app5-f1818__F">He is now much recovered from his illness, and is continually on the deck, apparently watching for the sledge that preceded his own. Yet, although un<pb n="032" xml:id="F1818_v1_044"/>happy, he is not so utterly occupied by his own misery, but that he interests himself deeply in the </seg>
               <seg xml:id="C06a_app6-f1818">employments </seg>
               <seg xml:id="C06a_app7-f1818">of others. He has </seg>
         
               <seg xml:id="C06b_app1-f1818">asked me many questions concerning my design; and I have related my little history frankly to him. He appeared pleased with the confidence, and suggested several alterations in my plan, which I shall find exceedingly useful. There is no pedantry in his manner; but all he does appears to spring solely from the interest he instinctively takes in the welfare of those who surround him. He is often overcome by </seg>
               <seg xml:id="C06b_app2-f1818">gloom, </seg>
               <seg xml:id="C06b_app3-f1818">and then he sits by himself, and tries to overcome all that is sullen or unsocial in his humour. These paroxysms pass from him like a cloud from before the sun, though his dejection never leaves him. </seg>
         
               <seg xml:id="C06c_app1-f1818">I have endeavoured to win his confidence; and I trust that I have suc<pb n="033" xml:id="F1818_v1_045"/>ceeded. One day I mentioned to him the desire I had always felt of finding a friend who might </seg>
               <seg xml:id="C06c_app2-f1818">sympathize </seg>
               <seg xml:id="C06c_app3-f1818">with me, and direct me by his counsel. I said, I did not belong to that class of men who are offended by advice. “I am self-educated, and perhaps I hardly rely sufficiently upon my own powers. I </seg>
               <seg xml:id="C06c_app4-f1818">wish therefore </seg>
               <seg part="I" xml:id="C06c_app5-f1818__I">that my companion should be wiser and more experienced than myself, to confirm and support me; nor have I believed it impossible to find a true friend.”</seg>
            </p>
            <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_div4_p28">
               <seg part="F" xml:id="C06c_app5-f1818__F">“I agree with you,” replied the stranger, “in believing that friendship is not only a desirable, but a possible acquisition. </seg>
         
               <seg part="I" xml:id="C06d_app1-f1818__I">I once had a friend, the most noble of human creatures, and am entitled, therefore, to judge respecting friendship. You have hope, and the world before you, and have no cause for despair. But I—I have lost <pb n="034" xml:id="F1818_v1_046"/>every thing, and cannot begin life anew.”</seg>
            </p>
            <seg part="M" xml:id="C06d_app1-f1818__M">
            <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_div4_p29">As he said this, his countenance became expressive of a calm settled grief, that touched me to the heart. But he was silent, and presently retired to his cabin.</p>
            </seg>
            <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_div4_p30">
               <seg part="F" xml:id="C06d_app1-f1818__F">Even broken in spirit as he is, no one can feel more deeply than he does the beauties of nature. The starry sky, the sea, and every sight afforded by these wonderful regions, seems still to have the power of elevating his soul from earth. Such a man has a double existence: he may suffer misery, and be overwhelmed by disappointments; </seg>
               <seg xml:id="C06d_app2-f1818">yet </seg>
               <seg part="I" xml:id="C06d_app3-f1818__I">when he has retired into himself, he will be like a celestial spirit, that has a halo around him, within whose circle no grief or folly ventures.</seg>
            </p>
            <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_div4_p31">
               <seg part="F" xml:id="C06d_app3-f1818__F">Will you </seg>
               <seg xml:id="C06d_app4-f1818">laugh </seg>
               <seg xml:id="C06d_app5-f1818">at the enthusiasm I express concerning this divine wan<pb n="035" xml:id="F1818_v1_047"/>derer? </seg>
         
               <seg part="I" xml:id="C06e_app1-f1818__I">If you do, you must have certainly lost that simplicity which was once your characteristic charm. Yet, if you will, smile at the warmth of my expressions, while I find every day new causes for repeating them.</seg>
            </p>
            <seg part="F" xml:id="C06e_app1-f1818__F"> 
            </seg>
         
            <seg part="I" xml:id="C06f_app1-f1818__I">
            </seg>
            <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_div4_p32">
               <seg part="F" xml:id="C06f_app1-f1818__F">August </seg>
               <seg xml:id="C06f_app2-f1818">19th, </seg>
               <seg part="I" xml:id="C06f_app3-f1818__I">17—.</seg>
            </p>
            <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_div4_p33">
               <seg part="F" xml:id="C06f_app3-f1818__F">Yesterday the stranger said to me, “You may easily perceive, Captain Walton, that I </seg>
               <seg xml:id="C06f_app4-f1818">have suffered </seg>
               <seg xml:id="C06f_app5-f1818">great and unparalleled misfortunes. I had determined, </seg>
               <seg xml:id="C06f_app6-f1818">once, </seg>
               <seg xml:id="C06f_app7-f1818">that the memory </seg>
               <seg xml:id="C06f_app8-f1818">of these </seg>
               <seg xml:id="C06f_app9-f1818">evils should die with me; but you have won me to alter my determination. You </seg>
               <seg xml:id="C06f_app10-f1818">seek for </seg>
               <seg xml:id="C06f_app11-f1818">knowledge and wisdom, as I once did; and I ardently hope that the gratification </seg>
               <seg xml:id="C06f_app12-f1818">of your </seg>
               <seg xml:id="C06f_app13-f1818">wishes may not be a serpent to sting you, as mine has been. I do not know that </seg>
               <seg xml:id="C06f_app14-f1818">the relation </seg>
               <seg xml:id="C06f_app15-f1818">of my </seg>
               <seg xml:id="C06f_app16-f1818">misfortunes </seg>
               <seg xml:id="C06f_app17-f1818">will be useful to </seg>
               <seg xml:id="C06f_app18-f1818">you, </seg>
               <seg xml:id="C06f_app19-f1818">yet, </seg>
               <seg xml:id="C06f_app20-f1818">if </seg>
         
               <seg xml:id="C06g_app1-f1818">you are inclined, <pb n="036" xml:id="F1818_v1_048"/>listen to my tale. I believe that the strange incidents connected with it will afford a view of nature, which may enlarge your faculties and understanding. You will hear of powers and occurrences, such as you have been accustomed to believe impossible: but I do not </seg>
         
               <seg xml:id="C06h_app1-f1818">doubt </seg>
               <seg part="I" xml:id="C06h_app2-f1818__I">that my tale conveys in its series internal evidence of the truth of the events of which it is composed.”</seg>
            </p>
            <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_div4_p34">
               <seg part="F" xml:id="C06h_app2-f1818__F">You may easily </seg>
               <seg xml:id="C06h_app3-f1818">conceive </seg>
               <seg part="I" xml:id="C06h_app4-f1818__I">that I was much gratified by the offered communication; yet I could not endure that he should renew his grief by a recital of his misfortunes. I felt the greatest eagerness to hear the promised narrative, partly from curiosity, and partly from a strong desire to ameliorate his fate, if it were in my power. I expressed these feelings in my answer.</seg>
            </p>
            <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_div4_p35">
               <seg part="F" xml:id="C06h_app4-f1818__F">“I thank you,” he replied, “for <pb n="037" xml:id="F1818_v1_049"/>your sympathy, but it is useless; my fate is nearly fulfilled. I wait but for one event, and then I shall repose in peace. I understand your feeling,” continued he, perceiving that I wished to interrupt him; “but you are mistaken, my friend, if thus you will allow me to name you; nothing can alter my destiny: listen to my history, and you will perceive how irrevocably it is </seg>
               <seg part="I" xml:id="C06h_app5-f1818__I">determined.</seg>
            </p>
            <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_div4_p36">
               <seg part="F" xml:id="C06h_app5-f1818__F">He </seg>
               <seg xml:id="C06h_app6-f1818">then told me, that he would commence his narrative the next day when I should be at leisure. This promise drew from me the warmest thanks. I have resolved every night, when I am not </seg>
               <seg xml:id="C06h_app7-f1818">engaged, </seg>
               <seg xml:id="C06h_app8-f1818">to record, as nearly as possible in his own words, what he has related during the day. If I should be engaged, I will at least make notes. This manuscript will doubtless afford you the greatest </seg>
               <seg xml:id="C06h_app9-f1818">pleasure: </seg>
               <seg xml:id="C06h_app10-f1818">but to me, <pb n="038" xml:id="F1818_v1_050"/>who know him, and who hear it from his own lips, with what interest and sympathy shall I read it in some future </seg>
               <seg part="I" xml:id="C06h_app11-f1818__I">day!</seg>
            </p>
            <seg part="F" xml:id="C06h_app11-f1818__F">
            <pb n="039" xml:id="F1818_v1_051"/>
            <head xml:id="novel1_letter4_div4_head3">FRANKENSTEIN;</head>
            <head xml:id="novel1_letter4_div4_head4">
               <hi xml:id="novel1_letter4_div4_head4_hi1">OR</hi>,</head>
            <head xml:id="novel1_letter4_div4_head5">THE MODERN PROMETHEUS.</head> 
            </seg>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>