<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-model href="../segMarkerTester.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Bridge Phase 5: Witness f1831, Collation unit C07</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Frankenstein Variorum Project</authority>
            <date>2018</date>
            <availability>
               <licence>Distributed under a Creative Commons
                                  Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License</licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Produced from collation output: 2018-10-01 10:15:03.568989 </p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="collation">
            <seg part="I" xml:id="C07a_app1-f1831__I">
            <milestone n="1" type="start" unit="chapter"/>
            </seg>
            <head xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter1_div4_div1_head1">
               <seg part="F" xml:id="C07a_app1-f1831__F">CHAPTER </seg>
               <seg part="I" xml:id="C07a_app2-f1831__I">I.</seg>
            </head>
            <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter1_div4_div1_p1">
               <seg part="F" xml:id="C07a_app2-f1831__F"> I </seg>
               <seg xml:id="C07a_app3-f1831">
               <hi xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter1_div4_div1_p1_hi1">AM</hi> by birth a Genevese; and my family is one of the most distinguished of that republic. My ancestors had been for many years counsellors and syndics; and my father had filled several public situations with honour and reputation. He was respected by all who knew </seg>
               <seg xml:id="C07a_app4-f1831">him, </seg>
               <seg xml:id="C07a_app5-f1831">for his integrity and indefatigable attention to public business. He passed his younger days perpetually occupied by the affairs of his country; </seg>
               <seg xml:id="C07a_app6-f1831">a variety of circumstances had prevented his marrying early, nor </seg>
               <seg xml:id="C07a_app7-f1831">was </seg>
               <seg xml:id="C07a_app8-f1831">it </seg>
               <seg xml:id="C07a_app9-f1831">until the decline of life that he </seg>
               <seg xml:id="C07a_app10-f1831">became a husband </seg>
               <seg xml:id="C07a_app11-f1831">and </seg>
               <seg xml:id="C07a_app13-f1831">the </seg>
               <seg part="I" xml:id="C07a_app14-f1831__I">father of a family.</seg>
            </p>
            <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter1_div4_div1_p2">
               <seg part="F" xml:id="C07a_app14-f1831__F">As </seg>
               <seg xml:id="C07a_app15-f1831">the circumstances of his marriage illustrate his character, I cannot refrain from relating them. One of his most intimate friends was a merchant, who, from a flourishing state, fell, through numerous mischances, into poverty. This man, whose name was Beaufort, was of a proud and unbending disposition, and could not bear to live in poverty and oblivion in the same country where he had formerly been distinguished for his rank and magni<pb n="19" xml:id="F1831_v_035"/>ficence. Having paid his debts, therefore, in the most honourable manner, he retreated with his daughter to the town of Lucerne, where he lived unknown and in wretchedness. My father loved Beaufort with the truest friendship, and was deeply grieved by his retreat in these unfortunate circumstances. He </seg>
               <seg xml:id="C07a_app16-f1831">bitterly deplored </seg>
               <seg xml:id="C07a_app17-f1831">the </seg>
               <seg xml:id="C07a_app18-f1831">false pride which led his friend to a conduct so little worthy </seg>
               <seg xml:id="C07a_app19-f1831">of </seg>
               <seg xml:id="C07a_app20-f1831">the affection that united them. He lost no time in endeavouring </seg>
               <seg xml:id="C07a_app21-f1831">to seek him </seg>
               <seg xml:id="C07a_app22-f1831">out, </seg>
               <seg xml:id="C07a_app23-f1831">with the hope of persuading </seg>
               <seg part="I" xml:id="C07a_app24-f1831__I">him to begin the world again through his credit and assistance.</seg>
            </p>
            <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter1_div4_div1_p3">
               <seg part="F" xml:id="C07a_app24-f1831__F">Beaufort had taken effectual measures to conceal himself; and it was ten months before my father discovered his abode. Overjoyed at this discovery, he hastened to the house, which was situated in a mean street, near the Reuss. But when he entered, misery and despair alone welcomed him. Beaufort had saved but a very small sum of money from the wreck of his fortunes; but it was sufficient to provide him with sustenance for some months, and in the mean time he hoped to procure some respectable employment in a merchant’s house. The interval </seg>
               <seg xml:id="C07a_app25-f1831">was, consequently, </seg>
               <seg part="I" xml:id="C07a_app26-f1831__I">spent in inaction; his grief only became more deep and rankling, when he had leisure for reflection; and at length it took so fast hold of his mind, that at the end of three months he lay on a bed of sickness, incapable of any exertion.</seg>
            </p>
            <seg part="M" xml:id="C07a_app26-f1831__M">
            <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter1_div4_div1_p4">His daughter attended him with the greatest tenderness; but she saw with despair that their little fund was rapidly decreasing, and that there was no other prospect of support. But Caroline Beaufort possessed a mind of an uncommon mould; and her courage rose to support her in her adversity. She procured plain work; she plaited straw; and by various means contrived to earn a pittance scarcely sufficient to support life.</p>
            </seg>
            <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter1_div4_div1_p5">
               <seg part="F" xml:id="C07a_app26-f1831__F">Several months passed in this manner. Her father grew worse; her time was more entirely occupied in attending him; her means of subsistence decreased; and in the tenth month her father died in her arms, leaving her an orphan and a beggar. This last blow overcame her; and she knelt by Beaufort’s coffin, weeping bitterly, when my father entered the chamber. He came like a protecting spirit to the <pb n="20" xml:id="F1831_v_036"/>poor girl, who committed herself to his </seg>
               <seg xml:id="C07a_app27-f1831">care; </seg>
               <seg xml:id="C07a_app28-f1831">and after the interment of his </seg>
               <seg xml:id="C07a_app29-f1831">friend, </seg>
               <seg part="I" xml:id="C07a_app30-f1831__I">he conducted her to Geneva, and placed her under the protection of a relation. Two years after this event Caroline became his wife.</seg>
            </p>
            <seg part="F" xml:id="C07a_app30-f1831__F"> 
            </seg>
         
            <seg xml:id="C07b_app1-f1831">
            <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter1_div4_div1_p6">There was a considerable difference between the ages of my parents, but this circumstance seemed to unite them only closer in bonds of devoted affection. There was a sense of justice in my father’s upright mind, which rendered it necessary that he should approve highly to love strongly. Perhaps during former years he had suffered from the late-discovered unworthiness of one beloved, and so was disposed to set a greater value on tried worth. There was a show of gratitude and worship in his attachment to my mother, differing wholly from the doating fondness of age, for it was inspired by reverence for her virtues, and a desire to be the means of, in some degree, recompensing her for the sorrows she had endured, but which gave inexpressible grace to his behaviour to her. Every thing was made to yield to her wishes and her convenience. He strove to shelter her, as a fair exotic is sheltered by the gardener, from every rougher wind, and to surround her with all that could tend to excite pleasurable emotion in her soft and benevolent mind. Her health, and even the tranquillity of her hitherto constant spirit, had been shaken by what she had gone through. During the two years that had elapsed previous to their marriage my father had gradually relinquished all his public functions; and immediately after their union they sought the pleasant climate of Italy, and the change of scene and interest attendant on a tour through that land of wonders, as a restorative for her weakened frame.</p> 
            <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter1_div4_div1_p7">From Italy they visited Germany and France. I, their eldest child, was born at Naples, and as an infant accompanied them in their rambles. I remained for several years their only child. Much as they were attached to each other, they seemed to draw inexhaustible stores of affection from a very mine of love to bestow them upon me. My mother’s tender caresses, and my father’s smile of benevolent pleasure while regarding me, are my first recollections. I was their plaything and their idol, and something better—<pb xml:id="F1831_v_037" n="21"/>their child, the innocent and helpless creature bestowed on them by Heaven, whom to bring up to good, and whose future lot it was in their hands to direct to happiness or misery, according as they fulfilled their duties towards me. With this deep consciousness of what they owed towards the being to which they had given life, added to the active spirit of tenderness that animated both, it may be imagined that while during every hour of my infant life I received a lesson of patience, of charity, and of self-control, I was so guided by a silken cord, that all seemed but one train of enjoyment to me.</p> 
            <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter1_div4_div1_p8">For a long time I was their only care. My mother had much desire to have a daughter, but I continued their single offspring. When I was about five years old, while making an excursion beyond the frontiers of Italy, they passed a week on the shores of the Lake of Como. Their benevolent disposition often made them enter the cottages of the poor. This, to my mother, was more than a duty; it was a necessity, a passion,—remembering what she had suffered, and how she had been relieved,—for her to act in her turn the guardian angel to the afflicted. During one of their walks a poor cot in the foldings of a vale attracted their notice, as being singularly disconsolate, while the number of half-clothed children gathered about it, spoke of penury in its worst shape. One day, when my father had gone by himself to Milan, my mother, accompanied by me, visited this abode. She found a peasant and his wife, hard working, bent down by care and labour, distributing a scanty meal to five hungry babes. Among these there was one which attracted my mother far above all the rest. She appeared of a different stock. The four others were dark-eyed, hardy little vagrants; this child was thin, and very fair. Her hair was the brightest living gold, and, despite the poverty of her clothing, seemed to set a crown of distinction on her head. Her brow was clear and ample, her blue eyes cloudless, and her lips and the moulding of her face so expressive of sensibility and sweetness, that none could behold her without looking on her as of a distinct species, a being heaven-sent, and bearing a celestial stamp in all her features.</p> 
            <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter1_div4_div1_p9"> 
               <pb xml:id="F1831_v_038" n="22"/>The peasant woman, perceiving that my mother fixed eyes of wonder and admiration on this lovely girl, eagerly communicated her history. She was not her child, but the daughter of a Milanese nobleman. Her mother was a German, and had died on giving her birth. The infant had been placed with these good people to nurse: they were better off then. They had not been long married, and their eldest child was but just born. The father of their charge was one of those Italians nursed in the memory of the antique glory of Italy,—one among the <hi xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter1_div4_div1_p9_hi1">schiavi ognor frementi</hi>, who exerted himself to obtain the liberty of his country. He became the victim of its weakness. Whether he had died, or still lingered in the dungeons of Austria, was not known. His property was confiscated, his child became an orphan and a beggar. She continued with her foster parents, and bloomed in their rude abode, fairer than a garden rose among dark-leaved brambles.</p> 
            <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter1_div4_div1_p10">When my father returned from Milan, he found playing with me in the hall of our villa, a child fairer than pictured cherub—a creature who seemed to shed radiance from her looks, and whose form and motions were lighter than the chamois of the hills. The apparition was soon explained. With his permission my mother prevailed on her rustic guardians to yield their charge to her. They were fond of the sweet orphan. Her presence had seemed a blessing to them; but it would be unfair to her to keep her in poverty and want, when Providence afforded her such powerful protection. They consulted their village priest, and the result was, that Elizabeth Lavenza became the inmate of my parents’ house—my more than sister—the beautiful and adored companion of all my occupations and my pleasures.</p> 
            </seg>
         
            <seg part="I" xml:id="C07c_app1-f1831__I">
            <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter1_div4_div1_p11">Every one loved Elizabeth. The passionate and almost reverential attachment with which all regarded her became, while I shared it, my pride and my delight. On the evening previous to her being brought to my home, my mother had said playfully,—“I have a pretty present for my Victor—to-morrow he shall have it.” And when, on the morrow, she presented Elizabeth to me as her promised gift, I, with childish seriousness, interpreted her words literally, and looked upon Elizabeth as mine—mine to protect, love, and <pb xml:id="F1831_v_039" n="23"/>cherish. All praises bestowed on her, I received as made to a possession of my own. We called each other familiarly by the name of cousin. No word, no expression could body forth the kind of relation in which she stood to me—my more than sister, since till death she was to be mine only.</p> 
            <milestone unit="chapter" type="end" n="1"/> 
            <milestone unit="chapter" type="start" n="2"/> 
            <head xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter2_div4_div2_head1">CHAPTER II.</head> 
            </seg>
            <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter2_div4_div2_p1">
               <seg part="F" xml:id="C07c_app1-f1831__F"> W<hi xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter2_div4_div2_p1_hi1">E</hi> were brought up together; there was not quite a year difference in our ages. I need not say that </seg>
         we were strangers to any species of disunion <seg xml:id="C07d_app11-f1831">or </seg>
               <seg xml:id="C07d_app12-f1831">dispute. Harmony was the soul of our companionship, and the diversity and contrast that subsisted </seg>in our <seg xml:id="C07d_app17-f1831">characters drew us nearer together. Elizabeth was of a calmer and more concentrated disposition; but, with all my ardour, </seg>
               <seg xml:id="C07d_app24-f1831">I was capable of a more intense application, and </seg>
               <seg xml:id="C07d_app25-f1831">was more deeply smitten with the thirst for knowledge.</seg>
               <seg xml:id="C07d_app26-f1831">She busied herself with following the aerial creations of the poets; and in the majestic and wondrous scenes which surrounded our Swiss home—the sublime shapes of the mountains; the changes of the seasons; tempest and calm; the silence of winter, and the life and turbulence of our Alpine summers,—she found ample scope for admiration and delight. </seg>
               <seg xml:id="C07d_app39-f1831">While my companion contemplated with a serious and satisfied spirit the magnificent appearances of things, I delighted in investigating their causes. </seg>The world was to me a <seg xml:id="C07d_app49-f1831">secret </seg>which I desired to <seg part="I" xml:id="C07d_app51-f1831__I">divine. Curiosity, earnest research to learn the hidden laws of nature, gladness akin to rapture, as they were unfolded to me, are among the earliest sensations I can remember.</seg>
            </p>
            <seg part="F" xml:id="C07d_app51-f1831__F"> 
            </seg>
            <seg part="I" xml:id="C07d_app58-f1831__I">
            </seg>
            <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter2_div4_div2_p2">
               <seg part="F" xml:id="C07d_app58-f1831__F">On the birth of a second son, my junior by seven years, my parents gave up entirely their wandering life, and fixed themselves in their native country. We possessed a house in Geneva, and a campagne on Belrive, the eastern shore of the lake, at the distance of rather more than a league from the city. We resided principally in the latter, and the lives of my parents were passed in considerable seclusion. It was my temper to avoid a crowd, and to attach myself fervently to a few. </seg>
         
               <seg xml:id="C07e_app1-f1831">I was indifferent, therefore, to my schoolfellows in general; </seg>
               <seg xml:id="C07e_app4-f1831">but I united myself in the bonds of the closest friendship to one among them. </seg>Henry <seg xml:id="C07e_app13-f1831">Clerval </seg>was the <seg xml:id="C07e_app15-f1831">son </seg>of a merchant <seg xml:id="C07e_app17-f1831">of </seg>
               <seg xml:id="C07e_app18-f1831">Geneva. </seg>He was a boy of singular talent <seg xml:id="C07e_app24-f1831">and fancy. He loved enterprise, hardship, even danger, for its own sake. </seg>
               <seg xml:id="C07e_app37-f1831">He was deeply read </seg>in books of <seg xml:id="C07e_app39-f1831">chivalry and romance. He composed heroic songs, and began to write many a tale of enchantment and knightly adventure. </seg>
               <seg part="I" xml:id="C07e_app44-f1831__I">He tried to make us act plays, and to enter into masquerades, the characters were drawn from the heroes of Roncesvalles, of the Round Table of King Arthur, and the chivalrous train who shed their blood to redeem the holy sepulchre from the hands of the infidels.</seg>
            </p>
            <seg part="F" xml:id="C07e_app44-f1831__F">
            </seg>
            <seg xml:id="C07e_app54-f1831">
            <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter2_div4_div2_p3">No human being could have passed a happier childhood than myself. My parents were possessed by the very spirit of kindness and indulgence. We felt that they were not the tyrants to rule our lot according to their caprice, but the agents and creators of all the many delights which we enjoyed. When I mingled with other families, I distinctly discerned how peculiarly fortunate my lot was, and gratitude assisted the developement of filial love.</p> 
            </seg>
            <seg xml:id="C07e_app131-f1831">
            <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter2_div4_div2_p4">My temper was sometimes violent, and my passions vehement; but by some law in my temperature they were turned, not towards childish pursuits, but to an eager desire to learn, and not to learn all things indiscriminately. I confess that neither the structure of languages, nor the code of governments, nor the politics of various states, possessed attractions for me. It was the secrets of heaven and earth that I desired to learn; and whether it was the outward substance of things, or the inner spirit of nature and the mysterious soul of man that occupied me, still my enquiries were directed to the metaphysical, or, in its highest sense, the physical secrets of the world.</p> 
            <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter2_div4_div2_p5">Meanwhile Clerval occupied himself, so to speak, with the moral relations of things. The busy stage of life, the virtues of heroes, and the actions of men, were his theme; and his hope and his dream was to become one among those <pb xml:id="F1831_v_041" n="25"/>whose names are recorded in story, as the gallant and adventurous benefactors of our species. The saintly soul of Elizabeth shone like a shrine-dedicated lamp in our peaceful home. Her sympathy was ours; her smile, her soft voice, the sweet glance of her celestial eyes, were ever there to bless and animate us. She was the living spirit of love to soften and attract: I might have become sullen in my study, rough through the ardour of my nature, but that she was there to subdue me to a semblance of her own gentleness. And Clerval—could aught ill entrench on the noble spirit of Clerval?—yet he might not have been so perfectly humane, so thoughtful in his generosity—so full of kindness and tenderness amidst his passion for adventurous exploit, had she not unfolded to him the real loveliness of beneficence, and made the doing good the end and aim of his soaring ambition.</p>
            </seg>
         
            <seg xml:id="C07f_app25-f1831"> 
            </seg>
         
            <seg part="I" xml:id="C07g_app1-f1831__I">
            </seg>
            <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter2_div4_div2_p6">
               <seg part="F" xml:id="C07g_app1-f1831__F">I feel </seg>
               <seg xml:id="C07g_app2-f1831">exquisite pleasure in dwelling on the recollections of childhood, before misfortune had tainted </seg>my <seg xml:id="C07g_app4-f1831">mind, and changed its bright visions </seg>of <seg xml:id="C07g_app6-f1831">extensive usefulness into gloomy </seg>and <seg xml:id="C07g_app8-f1831">narrow reflections upon self. </seg>
               <seg xml:id="C07g_app9-f1831">Besides, </seg>
               <seg xml:id="C07g_app10-f1831">in drawing the picture </seg>of <seg xml:id="C07g_app12-f1831">my early days, </seg>I <seg xml:id="C07g_app14-f1831">also </seg>
               <seg xml:id="C07g_app15-f1831">record those events which led, by insensible </seg>
               <seg xml:id="C07g_app16-f1831">steps, </seg>to <seg xml:id="C07g_app18-f1831">my after tale of misery: for when </seg>I <seg xml:id="C07g_app20-f1831">would account to myself for the birth </seg>of <seg xml:id="C07g_app22-f1831">that passion, which afterwards ruled my destiny, </seg>I <seg xml:id="C07g_app24-f1831">find it arise, like a mountain river, from ignoble and almost forgotten sources; but, swelling as it proceeded, it became the torrent which, in its course, has swept away all </seg>my <seg part="I" xml:id="C07g_app26-f1831__I">hopes and joys.</seg>
            </p>
            <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter2_div4_div2_p7">
               <seg part="F" xml:id="C07g_app26-f1831__F">Natural </seg>philosophy <seg xml:id="C07g_app28-f1831">is the genius that has </seg>regulated my <seg xml:id="C07g_app30-f1831">fate; </seg>I <seg xml:id="C07g_app32-f1831">desire, </seg>
               <seg xml:id="C07g_app33-f1831">therefore, </seg>in this <seg xml:id="C07g_app35-f1831">narration, </seg>to <seg xml:id="C07g_app37-f1831">state </seg>those facts which led to <seg xml:id="C07g_app40-f1831">my predilection </seg>for that science. When I was <seg xml:id="C07g_app43-f1831">thirteen </seg>years <seg xml:id="C07g_app45-f1831">of age, </seg>we all went on a party of pleasure to <seg xml:id="C07g_app48-f1831">the baths near Thonon: </seg>the <seg xml:id="C07g_app50-f1831">inclemency of the weather obliged us to remain a day </seg>confined to the inn. In this house I chanced to find a <seg xml:id="C07g_app53-f1831">volume </seg>of the works of Cornelius Agrippa. <seg xml:id="C07g_app55-f1831">I opened it with </seg>
               <seg xml:id="C07g_app56-f1831">apathy; the </seg>theory <seg xml:id="C07g_app58-f1831">which </seg>he <seg xml:id="C07g_app60-f1831">attempts </seg>to <seg xml:id="C07g_app62-f1831">demonstrate, </seg>and the wonderful facts <seg xml:id="C07g_app64-f1831">which he relates, </seg>soon changed this feeling <seg xml:id="C07g_app66-f1831">into </seg>enthusiasm. A new light <seg xml:id="C07g_app69-f1831">seemed to dawn </seg>upon my <seg xml:id="C07g_app71-f1831">mind; and, </seg>bounding with <seg xml:id="C07g_app73-f1831">joy, </seg>I communicated my discovery to my father. <seg xml:id="C07g_app76-f1831">
               <pb n="26" xml:id="F1831_v_042"/>My father looked </seg>carelessly at the <seg xml:id="C07g_app78-f1831">titlepage </seg>of my <seg xml:id="C07g_app80-f1831">book, </seg>
               <seg xml:id="C07g_app81-f1831">and </seg>
               <seg xml:id="C07g_app82-f1831">said, “Ah! </seg>Cornelius <seg xml:id="C07g_app84-f1831">Agrippa! </seg>My dear <seg xml:id="C07g_app86-f1831">Victor, </seg>do not waste your time upon <seg xml:id="C07g_app89-f1831">this; </seg>it is sad <seg part="I" xml:id="C07g_app91-f1831__I">trash.”</seg>
            </p>
            <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter2_div4_div2_p8">
               <seg part="F" xml:id="C07g_app91-f1831__F">If, </seg>instead of this <seg xml:id="C07g_app93-f1831">remark, </seg>my father had taken the pains to <seg xml:id="C07g_app95-f1831">explain </seg>to <seg xml:id="C07g_app97-f1831">me, </seg>that the principles of Agrippa had been entirely <seg xml:id="C07g_app99-f1831">exploded, </seg>and that <seg xml:id="C07g_app101-f1831">a modern system </seg>of science had been <seg xml:id="C07g_app104-f1831">introduced, </seg>which possessed much greater <seg xml:id="C07g_app107-f1831">powers </seg>than the <seg xml:id="C07g_app109-f1831">ancient, </seg>because the powers of the <seg xml:id="C07g_app112-f1831">latter </seg>were <seg xml:id="C07g_app114-f1831">chimerical, while those of the </seg>
               <seg xml:id="C07g_app115-f1831">former were </seg>real and practical; under such <seg xml:id="C07g_app117-f1831">circumstances, </seg>I should certainly have thrown Agrippa aside, <seg xml:id="C07g_app120-f1831">and </seg>
               <seg xml:id="C07g_app121-f1831">have contented </seg>my <seg xml:id="C07g_app123-f1831">imagination, </seg>warmed as it <seg xml:id="C07g_app125-f1831">was, </seg>
               <seg xml:id="C07g_app126-f1831">by returning with greater ardour </seg>to <seg xml:id="C07g_app131-f1831">my former studies. </seg>
               <seg xml:id="C07g_app138-f1831">It </seg>is even <seg xml:id="C07g_app140-f1831">possible, </seg>that the train of my ideas <seg xml:id="C07g_app142-f1831">would </seg>never have <seg xml:id="C07g_app144-f1831">received the </seg>fatal impulse <seg xml:id="C07g_app146-f1831">that </seg>led <seg xml:id="C07g_app148-f1831">to my ruin. But the </seg>cursory glance my father had taken of my volume by no means assured me that he was acquainted with <seg xml:id="C07g_app152-f1831">its </seg>contents; and I continued to read with the <seg xml:id="C07g_app155-f1831">greatest </seg>
               <seg part="I" xml:id="C07g_app156-f1831__I">avidity.</seg>
            </p>
            <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter2_div4_div2_p9">
               <seg part="F" xml:id="C07g_app156-f1831__F">When </seg>I returned home, my first care was to procure <seg xml:id="C07g_app159-f1831">the whole </seg>works of this <seg xml:id="C07g_app161-f1831">author, </seg>and afterwards <seg xml:id="C07g_app163-f1831">of Paracelsus and Albertus Magnus. I read and studied the wild fancies of these </seg>
               <seg xml:id="C07g_app164-f1831">writers </seg>with <seg xml:id="C07g_app166-f1831">delight; </seg>they appeared to me treasures known to few <seg xml:id="C07g_app169-f1831">beside </seg>
               <seg xml:id="C07g_app170-f1831">myself. </seg>
               <seg part="I" xml:id="C07g_app171-f1831__I">I have described myself as always having been embued with a fervent longing to penetrate the secrets of nature. In spite of the intense labour and wonderful discoveries of modern philosophers, I always came from my studies discontented and unsatisfied. Sir Isaac Newton is said to have avowed that he felt like a child picking up shells beside the great and unexplored ocean of truth. Those of his successors in each branch of natural philosophy with whom I was acquainted, appeared even to my boy’s apprehensions, as tyros engaged in the same pursuit.</seg>
            </p>
            <seg part="M" xml:id="C07g_app171-f1831__M">
            <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter2_div4_div2_p10">The untaught peasant beheld the elements around him, and was acquainted with their practical uses. The most learned philosopher knew little more. He had partially unveiled the face of Nature, but her immortal lineaments were still a wonder and a mystery. He might dissect, anatomise, and give names; but, not to speak of a final cause, causes their secondary and tertiary grades were <pb n="27" xml:id="F1831_v_043"/>utterly unknown to him. I had gazed upon the fortifications and impediments that seemed to keep human beings from entering the citadel of nature, and rashly and ignorantly I had repined.</p>
            </seg>
            <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter2_div4_div2_p11">
               <seg part="F" xml:id="C07g_app171-f1831__F">But here were books, and here were men who had penetrated deeper and knew more. I took their word for all that they averred, and I became their disciple. </seg>
               <seg xml:id="C07g_app206-f1831">It </seg>may appear <seg xml:id="C07g_app209-f1831">strange </seg>that <seg xml:id="C07g_app211-f1831">such </seg>should arise in the eighteenth <seg xml:id="C07g_app216-f1831">century; </seg>but <seg xml:id="C07g_app218-f1831">while I followed the routine of education in the schools of Geneva, I was, to a great degree, self taught with regard to my favourite studies. My father </seg>was not <seg xml:id="C07g_app220-f1831">scientific, </seg>and I <seg xml:id="C07g_app223-f1831">was left to struggle with a child’s blindness, added to a student’s thirst for knowledge. Under the guidance of my new preceptors, </seg>I entered with the <seg xml:id="C07g_app233-f1831">greatest </seg>diligence into the search of the <seg xml:id="C07g_app236-f1831">philosopher’s </seg>stone and the <seg xml:id="C07g_app238-f1831">elixir </seg>of <seg xml:id="C07g_app240-f1831">life; </seg>but the latter <seg xml:id="C07g_app242-f1831">soon obtained my </seg>
               <seg xml:id="C07g_app244-f1831">undivided </seg>
               <seg xml:id="C07g_app245-f1831">attention. </seg>Wealth was an inferior <seg xml:id="C07g_app247-f1831">object; </seg>but what <seg xml:id="C07g_app249-f1831">glory </seg>
               <seg xml:id="C07g_app250-f1831">would attend </seg>the <seg xml:id="C07g_app252-f1831">discovery, </seg>if I could <seg xml:id="C07g_app254-f1831">banish disease from the human </seg>
               <seg xml:id="C07g_app255-f1831">frame, </seg>and render man <seg xml:id="C07g_app257-f1831">invulnerable </seg>to <seg xml:id="C07g_app259-f1831">any but </seg>a violent <seg part="I" xml:id="C07g_app261-f1831__I">death!</seg>
            </p>
            <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter2_div4_div2_p12">
               <seg part="F" xml:id="C07g_app261-f1831__F">Nor </seg>were these my only <seg xml:id="C07g_app263-f1831">visions. </seg>The raising of ghosts or devils <seg xml:id="C07g_app266-f1831">was </seg>a promise liberally accorded <seg xml:id="C07g_app268-f1831">by my </seg>favourite <seg xml:id="C07g_app270-f1831">authors, </seg>the fulfilment of which I most eagerly <seg xml:id="C07g_app272-f1831">sought; and </seg>if my incantations were always <seg xml:id="C07g_app274-f1831">unsuccessful, I attributed </seg>the failure rather to my own inexperience <seg xml:id="C07g_app276-f1831">and mistake, than to a want of skill or fidelity in </seg>my <seg xml:id="C07g_app285-f1831">instructors. </seg>
               <seg xml:id="C07g_app287-f1831">And </seg>
               <seg xml:id="C07g_app288-f1831">thus for a time I </seg>was <seg xml:id="C07g_app299-f1831">occupied </seg>by <seg xml:id="C07g_app301-f1831">exploded systems, mingling, like </seg>an <seg xml:id="C07g_app304-f1831">unadept, </seg>a <seg xml:id="C07g_app309-f1831">thousand contradictory theories, and floundering desperately </seg>in <seg xml:id="C07g_app312-f1831">a very slough </seg>of <seg xml:id="C07g_app314-f1831">multifarious knowledge, guided by an ardent imagination </seg>and <seg xml:id="C07g_app319-f1831">childish reasoning, till an accident again changed the current of </seg>my <seg part="I" xml:id="C07g_app335-f1831__I">ideas.</seg>
            </p>
            <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter2_div4_div2_p13">
               <seg part="F" xml:id="C07g_app335-f1831__F">When </seg>I was about <seg xml:id="C07g_app337-f1831">fifteen </seg>years <seg xml:id="C07g_app340-f1831">old </seg>we <seg xml:id="C07g_app342-f1831">had retired to </seg>our house near <seg xml:id="C07g_app344-f1831">Belrive, </seg>when we witnessed <seg xml:id="C07g_app346-f1831">a </seg>
               <seg xml:id="C07g_app347-f1831">most </seg>violent and terrible <seg xml:id="C07g_app349-f1831">thunder-storm. </seg>It advanced from behind <seg xml:id="C07g_app351-f1831">the mountains of Jura; </seg>and the thunder <seg xml:id="C07g_app353-f1831">burst at once with </seg>
               <seg xml:id="C07g_app354-f1831">frightful </seg>
               <seg xml:id="C07g_app355-f1831">loudness from </seg>various quarters of the <seg xml:id="C07g_app357-f1831">heavens. </seg>I <seg xml:id="C07g_app359-f1831">remained, </seg>while the storm <seg xml:id="C07g_app361-f1831">lasted, watching </seg>its progress with curiosity and <seg xml:id="C07g_app364-f1831">delight. As </seg>I stood at the <seg xml:id="C07g_app366-f1831">door, on </seg>a sudden I beheld <seg xml:id="C07g_app368-f1831">a </seg>stream of fire issue from an old <seg xml:id="C07g_app371-f1831">and beautiful </seg>
               <seg xml:id="C07g_app372-f1831">oak, which stood </seg>about <seg xml:id="C07g_app374-f1831">twenty yards from </seg>our <seg xml:id="C07g_app376-f1831">
               <pb n="28" xml:id="F1831_v_044"/>house; </seg>and <seg xml:id="C07g_app378-f1831">so </seg>soon as the <seg xml:id="C07g_app380-f1831">dazzling light </seg>
               <seg xml:id="C07g_app381-f1831">vanished, the oak </seg>
               <seg xml:id="C07g_app382-f1831">had </seg>
               <seg xml:id="C07g_app383-f1831">disappeared, </seg>and <seg xml:id="C07g_app385-f1831">nothing remained </seg>but a <seg xml:id="C07g_app387-f1831">blasted </seg>
               <seg xml:id="C07g_app388-f1831">stump. </seg>When we visited it the next <seg xml:id="C07g_app391-f1831">morning, </seg>we found the <seg xml:id="C07g_app394-f1831">tree shattered in a </seg>singular manner. It was not splintered by the shock, but entirely reduced to thin <seg xml:id="C07g_app397-f1831">ribands </seg>of wood. <seg xml:id="C07g_app399-f1831">I never </seg>
               <seg xml:id="C07g_app400-f1831">beheld </seg>
               <seg xml:id="C07g_app401-f1831">anything </seg>so utterly <seg part="I" xml:id="C07g_app403-f1831__I">destroyed.</seg>
            </p>
            <seg part="F" xml:id="C07g_app403-f1831__F"> 
            </seg>
         
            <seg xml:id="C07h_app1-f1831">
            <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter2_div4_div2_p14">Before this I was not unacquainted with the more obvious laws of electricity. On this occasion a man of great research in natural philosophy was with us, and, excited by this catastrophe, he entered on the explanation of a theory which he had formed on the subject of electricity and galvanism, which was at once new and astonishing to me. All that he said threw greatly into the shade Cornelius Agrippa, Albertus Magnus, and Paracelsus, the lords of my imagination; but by some fatality the overthrow of these men disinclined me to pursue my accustomed studies. It seemed to me as if nothing would or could ever be known. All that had so long engaged my attention suddenly grew despicable. By one of those caprices of the mind, which we are perhaps most subject to in early youth, I at once gave up my former occupations; set down natural history and all its progeny as a deformed and abortive creation; and entertained the greatest disdain for a would-be science, which could never even step within the threshold of real knowledge. In this mood of mind I betook myself to the mathematics, and the branches of study appertaining to that science, as being built upon secure foundations, and so worthy of my consideration.</p> 
            <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter2_div4_div2_p15">Thus strangely are our souls constructed, and by such slight ligaments are we bound to prosperity or ruin. When I look back, it seems to me as if this almost miraculous change of inclination and will was the immediate suggestion of the guardian angel of my life— the last effort made by the spirit of preservation to avert the storm that was even then hanging in the stars, and ready to envelope me. Her victory was announced by an unusual tranquillity and gladness of soul, which followed the relinquishing of my ancient and latterly tormenting studies. It was thus that I was to be taught to associate evil with their prosecution, happiness with their disregard.</p> 
            <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter2_div4_div2_p16"> 
               <pb xml:id="F1831_v_045" n="29"/>It was a strong effort of the spirit of good; but it was ineffectual. Destiny was too potent, and her immutable laws had decreed my utter and terrible destruction.</p> 
            <milestone unit="chapter" type="end" n="2"/>
            </seg>
            <seg xml:id="C07h_app181-f1831"> 
            </seg>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>