<?xml version="1.1" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
      xmlns:fv="https://frankensteinvariorum.github.io"
      xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Bridge Phase 6: f1818 vol 2 chapter ix</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Frankenstein Variorum Project</authority>
            <date>2023—</date>
            <availability>
               <licence>Distributed under a Creative Commons
                                                  Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported
                                                  License</licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Produced from a corpus of collation output files for
                                                the Frankenstein Variorum digital edition on
                                                  2023-07-15T22:42:22.079808-04:00.</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <anchor type="semantic" subtype="start" xml:id="f1818_vol_2_chapter_ix"/>
         <seg xml:id="C23_app2-f1818">
            <milestone unit="chapter" type="start" n="16"/>
            <pb xml:id="F1818_v2_146" n="142"/>
         </seg>
         <seg xml:id="C23_app3-f1818">
            <head ana="start"/>CHAPTER IX.<head ana="end"/>
         </seg>
         <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter16_div4_div17_p1">
            <seg xml:id="C23_app5-f1818">T<hi xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter16_div4_div17_p1_hi1">HE</hi> being</seg> finished  <seg xml:id="C23_app7-f1818">speaking,</seg> and fixed his  <seg xml:id="C23_app9-f1818">looks</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C23_app10-f1818">upon</seg> me in expectation of a  <seg xml:id="C23_app12-f1818">reply. But I was</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C23_app13-f1818">bewildered, perplexed,</seg> and unable to arrange my ideas sufficiently to understand the  <seg xml:id="C23_app15-f1818">full extent</seg> of his proposition. He  <seg xml:id="C23_app17-f1818">continued—</seg>
         </p>
         <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter16_div4_div17_p2">
            <seg xml:id="C23_app19-f1818">“You</seg> must create a female for  <seg xml:id="C23_app21-f1818">me,</seg> with whom I can live in the interchange of those sympathies necessary for my  <seg xml:id="C23_app23-f1818">being.</seg> This you alone can  <seg xml:id="C23_app25-f1818">do; and I</seg> demand  <seg xml:id="C23_app27-f1818">it</seg> of you as a right which you must not  <seg xml:id="C23_app29-f1818">refuse.”</seg>
         </p>
         <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter16_div4_div17_p3">
            <seg xml:id="C23_app31-f1818">The latter part of his tale had kindled anew in me the anger that had <pb xml:id="F1818_v2_147" n="143"/>died away while he narrated his peaceful life among the cottagers, and,</seg> as he said  <seg xml:id="C23_app33-f1818">this,</seg> I could no longer suppress the  <seg xml:id="C23_app35-f1818">rage</seg> that burned within me.  <seg part="I" xml:id="C23_app37-f1818__I">
               </seg>
         </p>
         <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter16_div4_div17_p4">
            <seg part="F" xml:id="C23_app37-f1818__F"> “I</seg> do refuse  <seg xml:id="C23_app39-f1818">it,”</seg> I  <seg xml:id="C23_app41-f1818">replied; “and</seg> no torture shall ever extort a consent from  <seg xml:id="C23_app43-f1818">me.</seg> You may render me the most miserable of  <seg xml:id="C23_app45-f1818">men,</seg> but you shall never make me base in my own eyes. Shall I create another like  <seg xml:id="C23_app47-f1818">yourself,</seg> whose joint wickedness  <seg xml:id="C23_app49-f1818">might</seg> desolate the  <seg xml:id="C23_app51-f1818">world. Begone! I</seg> have answered  <seg xml:id="C23_app53-f1818">you;</seg> you may  <seg xml:id="C23_app55-f1818">torture me,</seg> but I will never  <seg xml:id="C23_app57-f1818">consent.”</seg>
         </p>
         <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter16_div4_div17_p5">
            <seg xml:id="C23_app59-f1818">“You</seg> are in the  <seg xml:id="C23_app61-f1818">wrong,”</seg> replied  <seg xml:id="C23_app63-f1818">the fiend; “and, instead</seg> of  <seg xml:id="C23_app65-f1818">threatening,</seg> I am content to reason with you. I am  <seg xml:id="C23_app67-f1818">malicious</seg> because I am  <seg xml:id="C23_app69-f1818">miserable;</seg> am I not shunned  <seg xml:id="C23_app71-f1818">and hated</seg> by all mankind?  <seg xml:id="C23_app73-f1818">You,</seg> my  <seg xml:id="C23_app75-f1818">creator,</seg> would tear me to  <seg xml:id="C23_app77-f1818">pieces,</seg> and  <seg xml:id="C23_app79-f1818">triumph; remember that,</seg> and tell me why I should pity man <pb xml:id="F1818_v2_148" n="144"/>more than he pities <seg xml:id="C23_app81-f1818">me?</seg> You would not call it  <seg xml:id="C23_app83-f1818">murder,</seg> if you  <seg xml:id="C23_app85-f1818">could precipitate</seg> me into one of those  <seg xml:id="C23_app87-f1818">ice-rifts, and destroy</seg> my frame, the work of your  <seg xml:id="C23_app89-f1818">own</seg> hands.   <seg xml:id="C23_app91-f1818">Shall I respect</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C23_app92-f1818">man,</seg> when he  <seg xml:id="C23_app94-f1818">contemns</seg> me? Let him live with me in the interchange of  <seg xml:id="C23_app96-f1818">kindness,</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C23_app97-f1818">and,</seg> instead of  <seg xml:id="C23_app99-f1818">injury,</seg> I would bestow every benefit upon him with tears of gratitude at his acceptance. But that cannot be;   <seg xml:id="C23_app102-f1818">the</seg> human senses are  <seg xml:id="C23_app104-f1818">insurmountable barriers to our union.</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C23_app105-f1818">Yet</seg> mine shall not  <seg xml:id="C23_app107-f1818">be</seg> the submission of abject slavery. I will revenge my  <seg xml:id="C23_app109-f1818">injuries:</seg> if I cannot inspire  <seg xml:id="C23_app111-f1818">love,</seg> I will cause  <seg xml:id="C23_app113-f1818">fear;</seg> and chiefly towards you my   <seg xml:id="C23_app116-f1818">arch-enemy,</seg> because my  <seg xml:id="C23_app118-f1818">creator,</seg> do I swear  <seg xml:id="C23_app120-f1818">inextinguishable hatred. Have a care:</seg> I will work  <seg xml:id="C23_app122-f1818">at your destruction,</seg> nor finish  <seg xml:id="C23_app124-f1818">until</seg> I desolate your  <seg xml:id="C23_app126-f1818">heart,</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C23_app127-f1818">so that you</seg> curse the hour of your birth.”  <seg part="I" xml:id="C23_app129-f1818__I">
               </seg>
         </p>
         <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter16_div4_div17_p6">
            <seg part="F" xml:id="C23_app129-f1818__F">
               </seg>
            <pb xml:id="F1818_v2_149" n="145"/>A <seg xml:id="C23_app131-f1818">fiendish</seg> rage animated him as he said this; his face was wrinkled into contortions too horrible for human eyes to behold; but presently he calmed  <seg xml:id="C23_app133-f1818">himself,</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C23_app134-f1818">and proceeded—</seg>
         </p>
         <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter16_div4_div17_p7">
            <seg xml:id="C23_app136-f1818">“I</seg> intended to reason. This passion is detrimental to  <seg xml:id="C23_app138-f1818">me;</seg> for you do not reflect  <seg xml:id="C23_app140-f1818">that you</seg> are the  <seg xml:id="C23_app142-f1818">cause</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C23_app143-f1818">of its</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C23_app144-f1818">excess.</seg> If any being felt emotions of benevolence towards  <seg xml:id="C23_app146-f1818">me,</seg> I should return  <seg xml:id="C23_app148-f1818">them</seg> an hundred and  <seg xml:id="C23_app150-f1818">an</seg> hundred fold; for that one  <seg xml:id="C23_app152-f1818">creature’s sake,</seg> I would make peace with the whole  <seg xml:id="C23_app154-f1818">kind!</seg> But I now indulge in dreams  <seg xml:id="C23_app156-f1818">of bliss</seg> that cannot be   <seg xml:id="C23_app158-f1818">realized.</seg> What I  <seg xml:id="C23_app160-f1818">ask of you is reasonable and</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C23_app161-f1818">moderate;</seg> I demand a creature of another  <seg xml:id="C23_app163-f1818">sex,</seg> but as hideous as  <seg xml:id="C23_app165-f1818">myself:</seg> the gratification is  <seg xml:id="C23_app167-f1818">small,</seg> but it is all that I can  <seg xml:id="C23_app169-f1818">receive,</seg> and it shall content me. It is  <seg xml:id="C23_app171-f1818">true,</seg> we shall be  <seg xml:id="C23_app173-f1818">monsters,</seg> cut off from all the  <seg xml:id="C23_app175-f1818">world;</seg> but on that account we shall be <pb xml:id="F1818_v2_150" n="146"/>more attached to one <seg xml:id="C23_app177-f1818">another.</seg> Our lives will not be  <seg xml:id="C23_app179-f1818">happy,</seg> but they will be  <seg xml:id="C23_app181-f1818">harmless,</seg> and free from the misery   <seg xml:id="C23_app184-f1818">I now feel. Oh! my</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C23_app185-f1818">creator,</seg> make me  <seg xml:id="C23_app187-f1818">happy;</seg> let me feel gratitude towards you for one  <seg xml:id="C23_app189-f1818">benefit!</seg> Let me see that I excite the sympathy of  <seg xml:id="C23_app191-f1818">some existing thing;</seg> do not deny me my  <seg xml:id="C23_app193-f1818">request!”</seg>
         </p>
         <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter16_div4_div17_p8"> I was moved. I shuddered when I thought of the possible consequences of my <seg xml:id="C23_app195-f1818">consent;</seg> but I felt that there was some justice in his argument. His  <seg xml:id="C23_app197-f1818">tale,</seg> and the feelings he now  <seg xml:id="C23_app199-f1818">expressed,</seg> proved him to be a creature of fine  <seg xml:id="C23_app201-f1818">sensations;</seg> and did  <seg xml:id="C23_app203-f1818">I not,</seg> as his   <seg xml:id="C23_app206-f1818">maker,</seg> owe him all the portion of happiness that it was in  <seg xml:id="C23_app208-f1818">my</seg> power to bestow? He saw my change of   <seg xml:id="C23_app210-f1818">feeling,</seg> and  <seg xml:id="C23_app212-f1818">continued—</seg>
         </p>
         <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter16_div4_div17_p9">
            <seg xml:id="C23_app214-f1818">“If</seg> you  <seg xml:id="C23_app216-f1818">consent,</seg> neither you  <seg xml:id="C23_app218-f1818">nor</seg> any  <seg xml:id="C23_app220-f1818">other</seg> human  <seg xml:id="C23_app222-f1818">being</seg> shall ever see us  <seg xml:id="C23_app224-f1818">
               <pb xml:id="F1818_v2_151" n="147"/>again:</seg> I will go to the vast wilds of  <seg xml:id="C23_app226-f1818">South</seg> America. My food is not that of man; I do not destroy the lamb  <seg xml:id="C23_app228-f1818">and</seg> the  <seg xml:id="C23_app230-f1818">kid,</seg> to glut my  <seg xml:id="C23_app232-f1818">appetite;</seg> acorns and berries afford me sufficient nourishment. My companion will be of the same nature as  <seg xml:id="C23_app234-f1818">myself,</seg> and will be content with the same fare. We shall make our bed of dried leaves; the sun will shine on us as on  <seg xml:id="C23_app236-f1818">man,</seg> and will ripen our food.  <seg xml:id="C23_app238-f1818">The picture I present to you is peaceful and</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C23_app239-f1818">human,</seg> and you must feel that you could deny it only in the  <seg xml:id="C23_app241-f1818">wantonness</seg> of power and cruelty. Pitiless as you  <seg xml:id="C23_app243-f1818">have been</seg> towards  <seg xml:id="C23_app245-f1818">me,</seg> I  <seg xml:id="C23_app247-f1818">now</seg> see compassion in your  <seg xml:id="C23_app249-f1818">eyes;</seg> let me seize the favourable  <seg xml:id="C23_app251-f1818">moment,</seg> and  <seg xml:id="C23_app253-f1818">persuade you to promise what I so ardently</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C23_app254-f1818">desire.”</seg>
         </p>
         <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter16_div4_div17_p10">
            <seg xml:id="C23_app256-f1818">“You propose,”</seg> replied I,  <seg xml:id="C23_app258-f1818">“to fly from</seg> the habitations of  <seg xml:id="C23_app260-f1818">man,</seg> to  <seg xml:id="C23_app262-f1818">dwell in</seg> those wilds where the beasts of the <pb xml:id="F1818_v2_152" n="148"/>field will be your only <seg xml:id="C23_app264-f1818">companions.</seg> How can  <seg xml:id="C23_app266-f1818">you,</seg> who long for the love and sympathy of  <seg xml:id="C23_app268-f1818">man,</seg> persevere in this exile? You will  <seg xml:id="C23_app270-f1818">return,</seg> and  <seg xml:id="C23_app272-f1818">again</seg> seek  <seg xml:id="C23_app274-f1818">their</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C23_app275-f1818">kindness,</seg> and you will meet  <seg xml:id="C23_app277-f1818">with</seg> their detestation; your evil  <seg xml:id="C23_app279-f1818">passions will be renewed, and you will then have a companion to aid you in</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C23_app280-f1818">the</seg> task of destruction.  <seg xml:id="C23_app282-f1818">This may not</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C23_app283-f1818">be;</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C23_app284-f1818">cease to argue the point, for</seg> I cannot  <seg xml:id="C23_app286-f1818">consent.”</seg>
         </p>
         <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter16_div4_div17_p11">
            <seg xml:id="C23_app288-f1818">“How</seg> inconstant are your  <seg xml:id="C23_app290-f1818">feelings!</seg> but a moment ago you were moved by my representations, and why do you again harden yourself to my complaints? I swear  <seg xml:id="C23_app292-f1818">to you,</seg> by the earth which I  <seg xml:id="C23_app294-f1818">inhabit,</seg> and by you that made  <seg xml:id="C23_app296-f1818">me, that,</seg> with the companion you  <seg xml:id="C23_app298-f1818">bestow,</seg> I will quit the neighbourhood of  <seg xml:id="C23_app300-f1818">man,</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C23_app301-f1818">and dwell,</seg> as it may chance, in the most savage  <seg xml:id="C23_app303-f1818">of</seg> places. My evil passions will have fled, for <pb xml:id="F1818_v2_153" n="149"/>I shall meet with <seg xml:id="C23_app305-f1818">sympathy;</seg> my life will flow quietly  <seg xml:id="C23_app307-f1818">away, and,</seg> in my dying  <seg xml:id="C23_app309-f1818">moments,</seg> I shall not curse my  <seg xml:id="C23_app311-f1818">maker.”</seg>
         </p>
         <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter16_div4_div17_p12"> His words had a strange effect upon me. I compassionated <seg xml:id="C23_app313-f1818">him, and sometimes</seg> felt a wish to console  <seg xml:id="C23_app315-f1818">him;</seg> but when I looked  <seg xml:id="C23_app317-f1818">upon him,</seg> when I saw the filthy mass that moved and  <seg xml:id="C23_app319-f1818">talked,</seg> my heart  <seg xml:id="C23_app321-f1818">sickened,</seg> and my feelings were altered to  <seg xml:id="C23_app323-f1818">those</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C23_app324-f1818">of</seg> horror and hatred. I tried to stifle  <seg xml:id="C23_app326-f1818">these sensations;</seg> I  <seg xml:id="C23_app328-f1818">thought,</seg> that as I could not  <seg xml:id="C23_app330-f1818">sympathize</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C23_app331-f1818">with him,</seg> I had no right to  <seg xml:id="C23_app333-f1818">withhold from</seg> him the small portion of happiness  <seg xml:id="C23_app335-f1818">which was yet</seg> in my power to bestow.  <seg part="I" xml:id="C23_app337-f1818__I">
               </seg>
         </p>
         <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter16_div4_div17_p13">
            <seg part="F" xml:id="C23_app337-f1818__F"> “You swear,”</seg> I said,  <seg xml:id="C23_app339-f1818">“to</seg> be  <seg xml:id="C23_app341-f1818">harmless;</seg> but have you not already  <seg xml:id="C23_app343-f1818">shewn</seg> a degree of  <seg xml:id="C23_app345-f1818">malice</seg> that  <seg xml:id="C23_app347-f1818">should</seg> reasonably make me distrust you? May not  <seg xml:id="C23_app349-f1818">even</seg> this be a feint that will  <seg xml:id="C23_app351-f1818">increase</seg>
            <pb xml:id="F1818_v2_154" n="150"/>your triumph <seg xml:id="C23_app353-f1818">by affording a wider scope</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C23_app354-f1818">for</seg> your  <seg xml:id="C23_app356-f1818">revenge?”</seg>
         </p>
         <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter16_div4_div17_p14">
            <seg xml:id="C23_app358-f1818">“How</seg> is  <seg xml:id="C23_app360-f1818">this?</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C23_app361-f1818">I thought</seg> I  <seg xml:id="C23_app363-f1818">had moved your compassion, and yet you still refuse to</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C23_app364-f1818">bestow on</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C23_app365-f1818">me the only benefit that can </seg>
            <seg xml:id="C23_app366-f1818">soften my </seg>
            <seg xml:id="C23_app367-f1818">heart,</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C23_app368-f1818">and render me harmless.</seg> If I have no ties and no  <seg xml:id="C23_app370-f1818">affections,</seg> hatred and vice must be my  <seg xml:id="C23_app372-f1818">portion;</seg> the love of another will destroy the cause of my  <seg xml:id="C23_app374-f1818">crimes,</seg> and I shall become a  <seg xml:id="C23_app376-f1818">thing,</seg> of whose existence every one will be ignorant. My vices are  <seg xml:id="C23_app378-f1818">the children of</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C23_app379-f1818">a</seg> forced solitude that I   <seg xml:id="C23_app381-f1818">abhor;</seg> and my virtues will necessarily arise when  <seg xml:id="C23_app383-f1818">I</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C23_app384-f1818">live in communion with</seg> an equal. I shall feel  <seg xml:id="C23_app386-f1818">the</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C23_app387-f1818">affections</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C23_app388-f1818">of a</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C23_app389-f1818">sensitive being, and become</seg> linked to the chain of existence and  <seg xml:id="C23_app391-f1818">events,</seg> from which I am now  <seg xml:id="C23_app393-f1818">excluded.”</seg>
         </p>
         <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter16_div4_div17_p15"> I paused some time <seg xml:id="C23_app395-f1818">to</seg> reflect on all he had   <seg xml:id="C23_app397-f1818">related,</seg> and the various argu<pb xml:id="F1818_v2_155" n="151"/>ments <seg xml:id="C23_app399-f1818">which</seg> he had   <seg xml:id="C23_app401-f1818">employed.</seg> I thought of  <seg xml:id="C23_app403-f1818">the</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C23_app404-f1818">promise of</seg> virtues which  he had displayed on the opening of his   <seg xml:id="C23_app407-f1818">existence,</seg> and  <seg xml:id="C23_app409-f1818">the</seg> subsequent blight  <seg xml:id="C23_app411-f1818">of all kindly</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C23_app412-f1818">feeling</seg> by the   <seg xml:id="C23_app415-f1818">loathing</seg> and  <seg xml:id="C23_app417-f1818">scorn which his</seg> protectors had manifested towards him. His power and threats were not  <seg xml:id="C23_app419-f1818">omitted</seg> in my  <seg xml:id="C23_app421-f1818">calculations:</seg> a creature who could exist  <seg xml:id="C23_app423-f1818">in</seg> the  <seg xml:id="C23_app425-f1818">ice caves</seg> of the  <seg xml:id="C23_app427-f1818">glaciers,</seg> and hide himself from  <seg xml:id="C23_app429-f1818">pursuit among</seg> the ridges  <seg xml:id="C23_app431-f1818">of</seg> inaccessible  <seg xml:id="C23_app433-f1818">precipices,</seg> was a being possessing faculties it would be vain to cope  <seg xml:id="C23_app435-f1818">with. After</seg> a long pause of  <seg xml:id="C23_app437-f1818">reflection,</seg> I  <seg xml:id="C23_app439-f1818">concluded,</seg> that the justice due both to him and my  <seg xml:id="C23_app441-f1818">fellow-creatures</seg> demanded of me that I should comply with his request. Turning to  <seg xml:id="C23_app443-f1818">him, therefore,</seg> I  <seg xml:id="C23_app445-f1818">said—</seg>
         </p>
         <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter16_div4_div17_p16">
            <seg xml:id="C23_app447-f1818">“I</seg> consent to your  <seg xml:id="C23_app449-f1818">demand,</seg> on  <seg xml:id="C23_app451-f1818">your</seg> solemn oath to quit Europe  <seg xml:id="C23_app453-f1818">for ever, and every</seg> other place in the neighbourhood <pb xml:id="F1818_v2_156" n="152"/>of <seg xml:id="C23_app455-f1818">man,</seg> as soon as I shall deliver into  <seg xml:id="C23_app457-f1818">your</seg> hands a female who  <seg xml:id="C23_app459-f1818">will</seg> accompany you in your  <seg xml:id="C23_app461-f1818">exile.”</seg>
         </p>
         <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter16_div4_div17_p17">
            <seg xml:id="C23_app463-f1818">“I swear,”</seg> he cried,  <seg xml:id="C23_app465-f1818">“by the sun, and by the blue sky of heaven,</seg> that  <seg xml:id="C23_app467-f1818">if you grant my prayer,</seg> while they exist you shall never behold  <seg xml:id="C23_app469-f1818">me again.</seg> Depart  <seg xml:id="C23_app471-f1818">to your</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C23_app472-f1818">home,</seg> and commence your  <seg xml:id="C23_app474-f1818">labours:</seg> I shall  <seg xml:id="C23_app476-f1818">watch their progress with</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C23_app477-f1818">unutterable</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C23_app478-f1818">anxiety;</seg> and fear not but that when you are ready  <seg xml:id="C23_app480-f1818">I shall</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C23_app481-f1818">appear.”</seg>
         </p>
         <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter16_div4_div17_p18"> Saying <seg xml:id="C23_app483-f1818">this,</seg> he suddenly quitted  <seg xml:id="C23_app485-f1818">me, fearful, perhaps,</seg> of any change in my sentiments. I saw him descend the mountain with greater speed than the flight of  <seg xml:id="C23_app487-f1818">an eagle,</seg> and quickly lost  <seg xml:id="C23_app489-f1818">him</seg> among the undulations of the sea of ice. </p>
         <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter16_div4_div17_p19"> His tale had occupied the whole <seg xml:id="C23_app491-f1818">day;</seg> and the sun was upon the  <seg xml:id="C23_app493-f1818">verge of the horizon when he departed. I knew <pb xml:id="F1818_v2_157" n="153"/>that I ought to hasten</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C23_app494-f1818">my descent towards</seg> the  <seg xml:id="C23_app496-f1818">valley,</seg> as I should soon be encompassed in  <seg xml:id="C23_app498-f1818">darkness;</seg> but my heart was heavy, and my steps slow. The labour of winding among the little paths  <seg xml:id="C23_app500-f1818">of the mountains,</seg> and fixing my feet firmly  <seg xml:id="C23_app502-f1818">as I</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C23_app503-f1818">advanced, perplexed me,</seg> occupied as I was by the  <seg xml:id="C23_app505-f1818">emotions</seg> which the   <seg xml:id="C23_app508-f1818">occurrences</seg> of the day had produced.  <seg xml:id="C23_app510-f1818">Night was far advanced,</seg> when I came to the  <seg xml:id="C23_app512-f1818">half-way resting-place,</seg> and seated myself beside the fountain. The stars shone at  <seg xml:id="C23_app514-f1818">intervals,</seg> as the  <seg xml:id="C23_app516-f1818">clouds passed from over</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C23_app517-f1818">them;</seg> the dark pines rose before  <seg xml:id="C23_app519-f1818">me,</seg> and every here and there a broken tree lay  <seg xml:id="C23_app521-f1818">on</seg> the   <seg xml:id="C23_app523-f1818">ground:</seg> it was a scene of wonderful  <seg xml:id="C23_app525-f1818">solemnity, and</seg> stirred strange thoughts within me. I wept  <seg xml:id="C23_app527-f1818">bitterly;</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C23_app528-f1818">and,</seg> clasping my hands in  <seg xml:id="C23_app530-f1818">agony,</seg> I  <seg xml:id="C23_app532-f1818">exclaimed, “Oh!</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C23_app533-f1818">stars,</seg> and clouds, and  <seg xml:id="C23_app535-f1818">winds,</seg> ye are all about  <seg xml:id="C23_app537-f1818">to mock</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C23_app538-f1818">
               <pb xml:id="F1818_v2_158" n="154"/>me:</seg> if ye really pity  <seg xml:id="C23_app540-f1818">me,</seg> crush  <seg xml:id="C23_app542-f1818">sensation and memory; let</seg> me  <seg xml:id="C23_app544-f1818">become as nought;</seg> but if  <seg xml:id="C23_app546-f1818">not, depart, depart</seg> and leave  <seg xml:id="C23_app548-f1818">me</seg>
            <seg part="I" xml:id="C23_app549-f1818__I">in darkness.” </seg>
         </p>
         <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter16_div4_div17_p20">
            <seg part="F" xml:id="C23_app549-f1818__F">
               </seg> These were wild and miserable  <seg xml:id="C23_app551-f1818">thoughts;</seg> but I cannot describe to you how the eternal twinkling of  <seg xml:id="C23_app553-f1818">the</seg> stars weighed upon me, and  <seg xml:id="C23_app555-f1818">how</seg> I listened to every blast of  <seg xml:id="C23_app557-f1818">wind,</seg> as  <seg xml:id="C23_app559-f1818">if</seg> it were a dull ugly siroc on its way to consume me. </p>
         <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter16_div4_div17_p21">
            <seg xml:id="C23_app563-f1818">Morning</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C23_app564-f1818">dawned</seg> before I arrived at the village of  <seg xml:id="C23_app566-f1818">Chamounix;</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C23_app567-f1818">but my</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C23_app568-f1818">presence,</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C23_app569-f1818">so haggard and</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C23_app570-f1818">strange,</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C23_app571-f1818">hardly calmed the fears of my</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C23_app572-f1818">family,</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C23_app573-f1818">who had waited the whole night in anxious expectation of my return.</seg>
            <seg part="I" xml:id="C23_app574-f1818__I">
               </seg>
         </p>
         <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter16_div4_div17_p22">
            <seg part="F" xml:id="C23_app574-f1818__F"> The following day we returned to Geneva. The</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C23_app575-f1818">intention of my father in coming had been to divert my</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C23_app576-f1818">mind,</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C23_app577-f1818">and to restore</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C23_app578-f1818">me</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C23_app579-f1818">to</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C23_app580-f1818">my lost</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C23_app581-f1818">tranquillity;</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C23_app582-f1818">but the</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C23_app583-f1818">medicine</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C23_app584-f1818">had been</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C23_app585-f1818">fatal. And,</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C23_app586-f1818">unable to account for the excess of <pb xml:id="F1818_v2_159" n="155"/>misery I appeared to</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C23_app587-f1818">suffer,</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C23_app588-f1818">he hastened to return</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C23_app589-f1818">home,</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C23_app590-f1818">hoping</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C23_app591-f1818">the quiet and</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C23_app592-f1818">monotony</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C23_app593-f1818">of a domestic life would by degrees alleviate my sufferings from</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C23_app594-f1818">whatsoever</seg>
            <seg part="I" xml:id="C23_app595-f1818__I">cause they might spring. </seg>
         </p>
         <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter16_div4_div17_p23">
            <seg part="F" xml:id="C23_app595-f1818__F"> For</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C23_app596-f1818">myself,</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C23_app597-f1818">I was passive in all their</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C23_app598-f1818">arrangements;</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C23_app599-f1818">and the gentle affection of my beloved Elizabeth was inadequate to draw me from the depth of my despair. The promise I had made to the dæmon weighed upon my</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C23_app600-f1818">mind,</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C23_app601-f1818">like</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C23_app602-f1818">Dante’s</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C23_app603-f1818">iron cowl on the</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C23_app604-f1818">heads</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C23_app605-f1818">of the hellish</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C23_app606-f1818">hypocrites.</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C23_app607-f1818">All pleasures of earth</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C23_app608-f1818">and</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C23_app609-f1818">sky passed</seg> before me  <seg xml:id="C23_app611-f1818">like</seg> a  <seg xml:id="C23_app613-f1818">dream,</seg> and that  <seg xml:id="C23_app615-f1818">thought only had to me the reality of life.</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C23_app616-f1818">Can you</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C23_app617-f1818">wonder,</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C23_app618-f1818">that sometimes a kind of insanity possessed</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C23_app619-f1818">me, or that I saw continually</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C23_app620-f1818">about me a multitude of filthy animals inflicting on me incessant</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C23_app621-f1818">torture,</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C23_app622-f1818">that often extorted</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C23_app623-f1818">screams</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C23_app624-f1818">and bitter groans?</seg>
            <seg part="I" xml:id="C23_app625-f1818__I">
               </seg>
         </p>
         <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter16_div4_div17_p24">
            <seg part="F" xml:id="C23_app625-f1818__F">
               <pb xml:id="F1818_v2_160" n="156"/>By</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C23_app626-f1818">degrees, however,</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C23_app627-f1818">these feelings became calmed. I entered again into the</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C23_app628-f1818">every-day scene</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C23_app629-f1818">of</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C23_app630-f1818">life,</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C23_app631-f1818">if not with</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C23_app632-f1818">interest,</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C23_app633-f1818">at least with some degree of tranquillity.</seg>
            <seg part="I" xml:id="C23_app634-f1818__I">
               </seg>
         </p>
         <seg part="F" xml:id="C23_app634-f1818__F">
            </seg>
         <seg xml:id="C23_app635-f1818">
            <milestone unit="chapter" type="end" n="16"/>
            <head ana="start"/>END OF VOL. II<head ana="end"/>
            <milestone unit="volume" n="3"/>
            <milestone unit="frontmatter" type="start" n="3"/>
         </seg>
         <seg xml:id="C23_app636-f1818">
            <milestone unit="frontmatter" type="end" n="3"/>
         </seg>
         <anchor type="collate" xml:id="C24"/>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
