<?xml version="1.1" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
      xmlns:fv="https://frankensteinvariorum.github.io"
      xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Bridge Phase 6: f1818 vol 3 chapter ii</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Frankenstein Variorum Project</authority>
            <date>2023—</date>
            <availability>
               <licence>Distributed under a Creative Commons
                                                  Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported
                                                  License</licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Produced from a corpus of collation output files for
                                                the Frankenstein Variorum digital edition on
                                                  2023-07-13T16:52:36.006315-04:00.</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <anchor type="semantic" subtype="end start" xml:id="f1818_vol_3_chapter_ii"/>
         <seg part="F" xml:id="C25_app35-f1818__F">
            <milestone unit="chapter" type="end" n="17"/>
            <milestone unit="chapter" type="start" n="18"/>
         </seg>
         <pb xml:id="F1818_v3_025" n="021"/>
         <seg xml:id="C25_app37-f1818">
            <head ana="start"/>CHAPTER II.<head ana="end"/>
         </seg>
         <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter18_div4_div20_p1">
            <seg xml:id="C25_app39-f1818">L<hi xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter18_div4_div20_p1_hi1">ONDON</hi>
            </seg> was  <seg xml:id="C25_app41-f1818">our present point of rest; we determined to remain several months in this wonderful and celebrated city.</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C25_app42-f1818">Clerval</seg> desired  <seg xml:id="C25_app44-f1818">the intercourse of the men of genius and talent who flourished at</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C25_app45-f1818">this</seg> time; but this  <seg xml:id="C25_app47-f1818">was</seg> with  <seg xml:id="C25_app49-f1818">me</seg> a secondary  <seg xml:id="C25_app51-f1818">object;</seg> I was principally occupied with the means of obtaining the information necessary for the completion of my  <seg xml:id="C25_app53-f1818">promise,</seg> and quickly availed myself of the letters of introduction that I had brought with  <seg xml:id="C25_app55-f1818">me,</seg> addressed to the  <seg xml:id="C25_app57-f1818">most</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C25_app58-f1818">distinguished natural philosophers.</seg>
            <seg part="I" xml:id="C25_app59-f1818__I">
               </seg>
         </p>
         <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter18_div4_div20_p2">
            <seg part="F" xml:id="C25_app59-f1818__F">
               </seg> If this journey had taken place during <pb xml:id="F1818_v3_026" n="022"/>my days of study <seg xml:id="C25_app61-f1818">and happiness,</seg> it would have afforded me inexpressible  <seg xml:id="C25_app63-f1818">pleasure. But a blight had come over my</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C25_app64-f1818">existence,</seg> and I only visited these people for the sake of the information they might give  <seg xml:id="C25_app66-f1818">me on the subject in which</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C25_app67-f1818">my interest</seg> was so  <seg xml:id="C25_app69-f1818">terribly profound.</seg> Company was  <seg xml:id="C25_app71-f1818">irksome</seg> to me; when  <seg xml:id="C25_app73-f1818">alone,</seg> I could fill my mind with the sights of heaven and earth; the voice of  <seg xml:id="C25_app75-f1818">Henry soothed</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C25_app76-f1818">me,</seg> and I could  <seg xml:id="C25_app78-f1818">thus</seg> cheat myself into  <seg xml:id="C25_app80-f1818">a transitory</seg> peace. But  <seg xml:id="C25_app82-f1818">busy uninteresting joyous</seg> faces brought back despair to  <seg xml:id="C25_app84-f1818">my heart.</seg> I saw an insurmountable  <seg xml:id="C25_app86-f1818">barrier placed</seg> between me and my  <seg xml:id="C25_app88-f1818">fellow-men;</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C25_app89-f1818">this barrier</seg> was sealed with the blood  <seg xml:id="C25_app91-f1818">of William</seg> and  <seg xml:id="C25_app93-f1818">Justine;</seg> and to reflect  <seg xml:id="C25_app95-f1818">on the</seg> events  <seg xml:id="C25_app97-f1818">connected with those names</seg> filled my soul with  <seg part="I" xml:id="C25_app99-f1818__I">anguish. </seg>
         </p>
         <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter18_div4_div20_p3">
            <seg part="F" xml:id="C25_app99-f1818__F"> But in Clerval</seg> I saw the image of my former self; he was  <seg xml:id="C25_app101-f1818">inquisitive,</seg> and an<pb xml:id="F1818_v3_027" n="023"/>xious to gain experience and <seg xml:id="C25_app103-f1818">instruction.</seg> The difference of manners  <seg xml:id="C25_app105-f1818">which</seg> he observed was to him   <seg xml:id="C25_app107-f1818">an inexhaustible source of</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C25_app108-f1818">instruction and amusement.</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C25_app109-f1818">He was for ever</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C25_app110-f1818">busy;</seg> and the only check to his enjoyments was my  <seg xml:id="C25_app112-f1818">sorrowful and</seg> dejected  <seg xml:id="C25_app114-f1818">mien.</seg> I tried to conceal this as much as  <seg xml:id="C25_app116-f1818">possible,</seg> that I might not debar him from the pleasures natural to  <seg xml:id="C25_app118-f1818">one</seg> who was entering on a new scene of life, undisturbed by any care or  <seg xml:id="C25_app120-f1818">bitter</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C25_app121-f1818">recollection. I often refused to accompany</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C25_app122-f1818">him, alleging</seg> another  <seg xml:id="C25_app124-f1818">engagement,</seg> that I might remain  <seg xml:id="C25_app126-f1818">alone.</seg> I now also began to collect the materials necessary for my  <seg xml:id="C25_app128-f1818">new</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C25_app129-f1818">creation,</seg> and this was  <seg xml:id="C25_app131-f1818">to me like the torture of single drops of water continually falling on the</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C25_app132-f1818">head.</seg> Every thought that was devoted to it was  <seg xml:id="C25_app134-f1818">an extreme anguish, and every word that I spoke in allusion to it <pb xml:id="F1818_v3_028" n="024"/>caused my lips to</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C25_app135-f1818">quiver,</seg> and my heart to  <seg xml:id="C25_app137-f1818">palpitate.</seg>
         </p>
         <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter18_div4_div20_p4"> After passing some months in <seg xml:id="C25_app139-f1818">London,</seg> we received a letter from a person in  <seg xml:id="C25_app141-f1818">Scotland,</seg> who had formerly been  <seg xml:id="C25_app143-f1818">our</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C25_app144-f1818">visitor</seg> at Geneva. He mentioned the beauties of his native  <seg xml:id="C25_app146-f1818">country, and</seg> asked us if those were not sufficient allurements to induce us to prolong our journey as far  <seg xml:id="C25_app148-f1818">north as</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C25_app149-f1818">Perth,</seg> where he resided.  <seg xml:id="C25_app151-f1818">Clerval</seg> eagerly desired to accept this  <seg xml:id="C25_app153-f1818">invitation;</seg> and I, although I abhorred society, wished to view again mountains and  <seg xml:id="C25_app155-f1818">streams,</seg> and all the  <seg xml:id="C25_app157-f1818">wondrous works</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C25_app158-f1818">with which</seg> Nature  <seg xml:id="C25_app160-f1818">adorns</seg> her chosen  <seg part="I" xml:id="C25_app162-f1818__I">dwelling-places. </seg>
         </p>
         <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter18_div4_div20_p5">
            <seg part="F" xml:id="C25_app162-f1818__F">
               </seg> We had arrived in  <seg xml:id="C25_app164-f1818">England</seg> at the beginning of   <seg xml:id="C25_app167-f1818">October,</seg> and it was now  <seg xml:id="C25_app169-f1818">February.</seg> We accordingly determined to commence our journey towards the north  <seg xml:id="C25_app171-f1818">at the expiration of another month. In this expedition we did not <pb xml:id="F1818_v3_029" n="025"/>intend to follow the great road to</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C25_app172-f1818">Edinburgh,</seg> but to visit Windsor, Oxford,  <seg xml:id="C25_app174-f1818">Matlock,</seg> and the Cumberland  <seg xml:id="C25_app176-f1818">lakes,</seg> resolving to arrive at the completion of this tour about the end of July. I packed  <seg xml:id="C25_app178-f1818">up</seg> my chemical  <seg xml:id="C25_app180-f1818">instruments,</seg> and the materials  <seg xml:id="C25_app182-f1818">I had</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C25_app183-f1818">collected,</seg> resolving to finish my labours in some obscure nook in the  <seg xml:id="C25_app185-f1818">northern highlands of Scotland.</seg>
         </p>
         <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter18_div4_div20_p6"> We quitted London on the <seg xml:id="C25_app187-f1818">27th</seg> of  <seg xml:id="C25_app189-f1818">March,</seg> and  <seg xml:id="C25_app191-f1818">remained</seg> a few days at  <seg xml:id="C25_app193-f1818">Windsor,</seg> rambling in its beautiful forest. This was a new scene to us mountaineers; the  <seg xml:id="C25_app195-f1818">majestic oaks,</seg> the quantity of  <seg xml:id="C25_app197-f1818">game,</seg> and the  <seg xml:id="C25_app199-f1818">herds</seg> of  <seg xml:id="C25_app201-f1818">stately deer,</seg> were all novelties to us.  <seg part="I" xml:id="C25_app203-f1818__I">
               </seg>
         </p>
         <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter18_div4_div20_p7">
            <seg part="F" xml:id="C25_app203-f1818__F">
               </seg> From thence we proceeded to Oxford.  <seg xml:id="C25_app205-f1818">As</seg> we  <seg xml:id="C25_app207-f1818">entered this city, our minds</seg> were  <seg xml:id="C25_app209-f1818">filled</seg> with the  <seg xml:id="C25_app211-f1818">remembrance</seg> of the  <seg xml:id="C25_app213-f1818">events that had been transacted there more than a century</seg> and  <seg xml:id="C25_app215-f1818">a half <pb xml:id="F1818_v3_030" n="026"/>before. It was here that Charles I. had collected his forces. This city had remained faithful to him, after</seg> the  <seg xml:id="C25_app217-f1818">whole nation</seg> had  <seg xml:id="C25_app219-f1818">forsaken his cause</seg> to  <seg xml:id="C25_app221-f1818">join</seg> the  <seg xml:id="C25_app223-f1818">standard of parliament</seg> and  <seg xml:id="C25_app225-f1818">liberty.</seg> The  <seg xml:id="C25_app227-f1818">memory</seg> of  <seg xml:id="C25_app229-f1818">that unfortunate king, and his companions,</seg> the  <seg xml:id="C25_app231-f1818">amiable Falkland, the insolent</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C25_app232-f1818">Gower,</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C25_app233-f1818">his queen, and son, gave</seg> a  <seg xml:id="C25_app235-f1818">peculiar interest to every part</seg> of  <seg xml:id="C25_app237-f1818">the city, which they might be supposed to have inhabited.</seg> The  <seg xml:id="C25_app239-f1818">spirit</seg> of  <seg xml:id="C25_app241-f1818">elder days found a dwelling here,</seg> and  <seg xml:id="C25_app243-f1818">we delighted to trace its footsteps. If these feelings had not found an imaginary gratification,</seg> the  <seg xml:id="C25_app245-f1818">appearance</seg> of  <seg xml:id="C25_app247-f1818">the city had yet</seg> in  <seg xml:id="C25_app249-f1818">itself sufficient beauty to obtain our admiration.</seg> The  <seg xml:id="C25_app251-f1818">colleges are ancient and picturesque;</seg> the  <seg xml:id="C25_app253-f1818">streets are almost magnificent; and</seg> the  <seg xml:id="C25_app255-f1818">lovely Isis, which flows beside</seg> it  <seg xml:id="C25_app257-f1818">through meadows</seg> of  <seg part="I" xml:id="C25_app259-f1818__I">exquisite verdure, is spread forth into a <pb xml:id="F1818_v3_031" n="027"/>placid expanse of waters, which reflects its majestic assemblage of towers, and spires, and domes, embosomed among aged trees. </seg>
         </p>
         <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter18_div4_div20_p8">
            <seg part="F" xml:id="C25_app259-f1818__F"> I enjoyed this scene; and yet my enjoyment was embittered both by</seg> the  <seg xml:id="C25_app261-f1818">memory</seg> of  <seg xml:id="C25_app263-f1818">the</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C25_app264-f1818">past, and the anticipation of the future. I was formed for peaceful happiness. During my youthful days discontent never visited my mind; and if I was ever overcome by <hi xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter18_div4_div20_p8_hi1">ennui</hi>,</seg> the  <seg xml:id="C25_app266-f1818">sight</seg> of  <seg xml:id="C25_app268-f1818">what is beautiful</seg> in  <seg xml:id="C25_app270-f1818">nature, or</seg> the  <seg xml:id="C25_app272-f1818">study of what is excellent and sublime in</seg> the  <seg xml:id="C25_app274-f1818">productions</seg> of  <seg xml:id="C25_app276-f1818">man, could always interest my heart, and communicate elasticity to my spirits. But I am a blasted tree; the bolt has entered my soul; and I felt then</seg> that  <seg xml:id="C25_app278-f1818">I</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C25_app279-f1818">should survive to exhibit, what I shall soon cease</seg> to  <seg xml:id="C25_app281-f1818">be—a miserable spectacle of wrecked humanity, pitiable</seg> to  <seg xml:id="C25_app283-f1818">others,</seg> and  <seg xml:id="C25_app285-f1818">abhorrent</seg> to  <seg part="I" xml:id="C25_app287-f1818__I">myself. </seg>
         </p>
         <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter18_div4_div20_p9">
            <seg part="F" xml:id="C25_app287-f1818__F">
               </seg>
            <pb xml:id="F1818_v3_032" n="028"/>We <seg xml:id="C25_app289-f1818">passed a considerable period at Oxford, rambling among its environs, and endeavouring to identify every spot which might relate to</seg> the  <seg xml:id="C25_app291-f1818">most animating epoch of English history. Our little voyages of discovery were often prolonged by</seg> the  <seg xml:id="C25_app293-f1818">successive objects that presented themselves.</seg> We  <seg xml:id="C25_app295-f1818">visited the tomb of the illustrious Hampden,</seg> and  <seg xml:id="C25_app297-f1818">the field on which that patriot fell. For a moment my soul was elevated from its debasing and miserable</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C25_app298-f1818">fears</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C25_app299-f1818">to contemplate</seg> the  <seg xml:id="C25_app301-f1818">divine ideas</seg> of  <seg xml:id="C25_app303-f1818">liberty and</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C25_app304-f1818">self-sacrifice,</seg> of  <seg xml:id="C25_app306-f1818">which</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C25_app307-f1818">these sights were the monuments and</seg> the  <seg xml:id="C25_app309-f1818">remembrancers. For an instant I dared to shake off my chains, and look around me with</seg> a  <seg part="I" xml:id="C25_app311-f1818__I">free and lofty spirit; but the iron had eaten into my flesh, and I sank again, trembling and hopeless, into my miserable self. </seg>
         </p>
         <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter18_div4_div20_p10">
            <seg part="F" xml:id="C25_app311-f1818__F">
               </seg> We  <seg xml:id="C25_app313-f1818">left Oxford with regret,</seg> and  <seg xml:id="C25_app315-f1818">pro<pb xml:id="F1818_v3_033" n="029"/>ceeded to</seg> Matlock, which was our next place  <seg xml:id="C25_app317-f1818">of rest. The country in the neighbourhood of this village resembled,</seg> to a  <seg xml:id="C25_app319-f1818">greater degree,</seg> the scenery of Switzerland; but every thing is on a lower  <seg xml:id="C25_app321-f1818">scale,</seg> and the green  <seg xml:id="C25_app323-f1818">hills want the</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C25_app324-f1818">crown</seg> of distant white   <seg xml:id="C25_app326-f1818">Alps,</seg> which always attend on the piny  <seg xml:id="C25_app328-f1818">mountains</seg> of  <seg xml:id="C25_app330-f1818">my native</seg> country. We visited the wondrous  <seg xml:id="C25_app332-f1818">cave,</seg> and the  <seg xml:id="C25_app334-f1818">little cabinets of natural</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C25_app335-f1818">history,</seg> where the curiosities are disposed in the same manner as in the collections at Servox  <seg xml:id="C25_app337-f1818">and Chamounix.</seg> The latter  <seg xml:id="C25_app339-f1818">name</seg> made me  <seg xml:id="C25_app341-f1818">tremble,</seg> when pronounced by  <seg xml:id="C25_app343-f1818">Henry;</seg> and I hastened to quit  <seg xml:id="C25_app345-f1818">Matlock, with which that terrible scene was thus associated.</seg>
         </p>
         <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter18_div4_div20_p11"> From <seg xml:id="C25_app347-f1818">Derby</seg> still journeying  <seg xml:id="C25_app349-f1818">northward,</seg> we passed two months  <seg xml:id="C25_app351-f1818">in</seg> Cumberland and   <seg xml:id="C25_app353-f1818">Westmoreland.</seg> I could now almost fancy myself among the <pb xml:id="F1818_v3_034" n="030"/>Swiss <seg xml:id="C25_app355-f1818">mountains.</seg> The little patches of snow which yet lingered  <seg xml:id="C25_app357-f1818">on</seg> the  <seg xml:id="C25_app359-f1818">northern</seg> sides of the  <seg xml:id="C25_app361-f1818">mountains,</seg> the  <seg xml:id="C25_app363-f1818">lakes,</seg> and the dashing of the rocky  <seg xml:id="C25_app365-f1818">streams,</seg> were all  <seg xml:id="C25_app367-f1818">familiar and dear sights to me. Here also we made some</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C25_app368-f1818">acquaintances,</seg> who almost contrived to cheat me into happiness. The delight of  <seg xml:id="C25_app370-f1818">Clerval</seg> was proportionably greater than mine; his mind expanded in the company of men of  <seg xml:id="C25_app372-f1818">talent,</seg> and he found in  <seg xml:id="C25_app374-f1818">his own nature</seg> greater  <seg xml:id="C25_app376-f1818">capacities</seg> and  <seg xml:id="C25_app378-f1818">resources</seg> than he could  <seg xml:id="C25_app380-f1818">have</seg> imagined himself to have possessed while he associated with his inferiors. “I could pass my life here,” said he to   <seg xml:id="C25_app382-f1818">me;</seg> “and among these mountains I should  <seg xml:id="C25_app384-f1818">scarcely</seg> regret Switzerland and the  <seg xml:id="C25_app386-f1818">Rhine.”</seg>
         </p>
         <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter18_div4_div20_p12"> But he found that a <seg xml:id="C25_app388-f1818">traveller’s</seg> life is  <seg xml:id="C25_app390-f1818">one that includes much pain amidst its enjoyments. His feelings</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C25_app391-f1818">are</seg> for ever on the   <seg xml:id="C25_app393-f1818">stretch;</seg> and when he  <seg xml:id="C25_app395-f1818">be<pb xml:id="F1818_v3_035" n="031"/>gins</seg> to sink into  <seg xml:id="C25_app397-f1818">repose,</seg> he  <seg xml:id="C25_app399-f1818">finds</seg> himself obliged  <seg xml:id="C25_app401-f1818">to quit</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C25_app402-f1818">that on which he rests in pleasure</seg> for something  <seg xml:id="C25_app404-f1818">new,</seg> which again  <seg xml:id="C25_app406-f1818">engages</seg> his  <seg xml:id="C25_app408-f1818">attention, and</seg> which  <seg xml:id="C25_app410-f1818">also he</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C25_app411-f1818">forsakes</seg> for  <seg xml:id="C25_app413-f1818">other</seg>
            <seg part="I" xml:id="C25_app414-f1818__I">novelties. </seg>
         </p>
         <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter18_div4_div20_p13">
            <seg part="F" xml:id="C25_app414-f1818__F">
               </seg> We had scarcely visited the various lakes of Cumberland  <seg xml:id="C25_app416-f1818">and</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C25_app417-f1818">Westmoreland,</seg> and conceived an affection for some of the  <seg xml:id="C25_app419-f1818">inhabitants,</seg> when the period of our appointment with our Scotch friend  <seg xml:id="C25_app421-f1818">approached,</seg> and we left  <seg xml:id="C25_app423-f1818">them</seg> to travel on. For my own part I was not sorry. I had now neglected my promise for some  <seg xml:id="C25_app425-f1818">time,</seg> and I feared the effects of the  <seg xml:id="C25_app427-f1818">dæmon’s</seg> disappointment. He might remain in  <seg xml:id="C25_app429-f1818">Switzerland,</seg> and  <seg xml:id="C25_app431-f1818">wreak</seg> his vengeance  <seg xml:id="C25_app433-f1818">on</seg> my  <seg xml:id="C25_app435-f1818">relatives.</seg> This idea  <seg xml:id="C25_app437-f1818">pursued me,</seg> and tormented me at every moment  <seg xml:id="C25_app439-f1818">from which</seg> I might otherwise have snatched repose and peace. I waited for my letters with feverish  <seg xml:id="C25_app441-f1818">im<pb xml:id="F1818_v3_036" n="032"/>patience:</seg> if they were  <seg xml:id="C25_app443-f1818">delayed,</seg> I was  <seg xml:id="C25_app445-f1818">miserable,</seg> and overcome by a thousand fears; and when they  <seg xml:id="C25_app447-f1818">arrived,</seg> and I saw the superscription of Elizabeth or my  <seg xml:id="C25_app449-f1818">father,</seg> I hardly dared to read  <seg xml:id="C25_app451-f1818">and ascertain</seg> my fate. Sometimes I thought that the fiend followed  <seg xml:id="C25_app453-f1818">me,</seg> and might  <seg xml:id="C25_app455-f1818">expedite my remissness</seg> by murdering my   <seg xml:id="C25_app458-f1818">companion.</seg> When these   <seg xml:id="C25_app461-f1818">thoughts possessed me,</seg> I would not quit Henry for a  <seg xml:id="C25_app463-f1818">moment,</seg> but followed him as his  <seg xml:id="C25_app465-f1818">shadow,</seg> to protect him from  <seg xml:id="C25_app467-f1818">the</seg> fancied rage of his destroyer. I felt as if I had committed some great   <seg xml:id="C25_app469-f1818">crime,</seg> the consciousness of which haunted me. I was  <seg xml:id="C25_app471-f1818">guiltless,</seg> but I had  <seg xml:id="C25_app473-f1818">indeed</seg> drawn down a horrible curse   <seg xml:id="C25_app475-f1818">upon</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C25_app476-f1818">my</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C25_app477-f1818">head,</seg> as mortal as that of  <seg xml:id="C25_app479-f1818">crime.</seg>
         </p>
         <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter18_div4_div20_p14"> I visited Edinburgh with languid eyes and <seg xml:id="C25_app481-f1818">mind;</seg> and yet that city might have  <seg xml:id="C25_app483-f1818">interested</seg> the most unfortunate being.  <seg xml:id="C25_app485-f1818">Clerval</seg> did not like it so well <pb xml:id="F1818_v3_037" n="033"/>as <seg xml:id="C25_app487-f1818">Oxford;</seg> for the antiquity of  <seg xml:id="C25_app489-f1818">the</seg> latter city was   <seg xml:id="C25_app492-f1818">more</seg> pleasing to him. But the beauty  <seg xml:id="C25_app494-f1818">and regularity</seg> of the new town  <seg xml:id="C25_app496-f1818">of</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C25_app497-f1818">Edinburgh, its romantic castle, and</seg> its  <seg xml:id="C25_app499-f1818">environs,</seg> the most  <seg xml:id="C25_app501-f1818">delightful</seg> in the  <seg xml:id="C25_app503-f1818">world, Arthur’s</seg> Seat,  <seg xml:id="C25_app505-f1818">St. Bernard’s Well,</seg> and the Pentland  <seg xml:id="C25_app507-f1818">Hills, compensated him for the change, and filled him with cheerfulness and admiration.</seg> But I was impatient to arrive at the termination of my journey.  <seg part="I" xml:id="C25_app509-f1818__I">
               </seg>
         </p>
         <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter18_div4_div20_p15">
            <seg part="F" xml:id="C25_app509-f1818__F">
               </seg> We left  <seg xml:id="C25_app511-f1818">Edinburgh</seg> in a  <seg xml:id="C25_app513-f1818">week,</seg> passing through  <seg xml:id="C25_app515-f1818">Coupar,</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C25_app516-f1818">St.</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C25_app517-f1818">Andrews,</seg> and along  <seg xml:id="C25_app519-f1818">the banks of the</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C25_app520-f1818">Tay,</seg> to  <seg xml:id="C25_app522-f1818">Perth,</seg> where our friend expected  <seg xml:id="C25_app524-f1818">us.</seg> But I was  <seg xml:id="C25_app526-f1818">in</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C25_app527-f1818">no</seg> mood to laugh and talk with  <seg xml:id="C25_app529-f1818">strangers,</seg> or enter into their feelings or plans with  <seg xml:id="C25_app531-f1818">the</seg> good humour expected from a   <seg xml:id="C25_app533-f1818">guest;</seg> and accordingly I told  <seg xml:id="C25_app535-f1818">Clerval</seg> that I wished to make the tour of Scotland  <seg xml:id="C25_app537-f1818">alone. “Do <pb xml:id="F1818_v3_038" n="034"/>you,”</seg> said I,  <seg xml:id="C25_app539-f1818">“enjoy yourself,</seg> and let this be our  <seg xml:id="C25_app541-f1818">rendezvous.</seg> I may be absent a month or  <seg xml:id="C25_app543-f1818">two;</seg> but do not interfere with my  <seg xml:id="C25_app545-f1818">motions,</seg> I entreat  <seg xml:id="C25_app547-f1818">you:</seg> leave  <seg xml:id="C25_app549-f1818">me</seg> to peace and solitude for a short   <seg xml:id="C25_app551-f1818">time;</seg> and when I  <seg xml:id="C25_app553-f1818">return,</seg> I hope it will be with a lighter  <seg xml:id="C25_app555-f1818">heart,</seg> more congenial to your own temper.”  <seg part="I" xml:id="C25_app557-f1818__I">
               </seg>
         </p>
         <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter18_div4_div20_p16">
            <seg part="F" xml:id="C25_app557-f1818__F">
               </seg> Henry wished to dissuade  <seg xml:id="C25_app559-f1818">me; but,</seg> seeing me bent on this  <seg xml:id="C25_app561-f1818">plan,</seg> ceased to remonstrate.  <seg xml:id="C25_app563-f1818">He</seg> entreated me to write often.   <seg xml:id="C25_app565-f1818">“I</seg> had rather be with  <seg xml:id="C25_app567-f1818">you,”</seg> he said,  <seg xml:id="C25_app569-f1818">“in</seg> your solitary  <seg xml:id="C25_app571-f1818">rambles,</seg> than with these Scotch  <seg xml:id="C25_app573-f1818">people,</seg> whom I do not  <seg xml:id="C25_app575-f1818">know:</seg> hasten  <seg xml:id="C25_app577-f1818">then,</seg> my dear  <seg xml:id="C25_app579-f1818">friend,</seg> to  <seg xml:id="C25_app581-f1818">return,</seg> that I may again feel myself  <seg xml:id="C25_app583-f1818">somewhat at</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C25_app584-f1818">home,</seg> which I cannot do in your  <seg xml:id="C25_app586-f1818">absence.”</seg>
         </p>
         <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter18_div4_div20_p17"> Having parted from my <seg xml:id="C25_app588-f1818">friend,</seg> I  <seg xml:id="C25_app590-f1818">determined</seg> to visit some remote spot of  <seg xml:id="C25_app592-f1818">Scotland,</seg> and finish my work in solitude. I did not doubt but that the <pb xml:id="F1818_v3_039" n="035"/>monster followed me, and would <seg xml:id="C25_app594-f1818">discover himself to</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C25_app595-f1818">me</seg> when I should have finished,  <seg xml:id="C25_app597-f1818">that he might</seg> receive his companion.   <seg part="I" xml:id="C25_app599-f1818__I">
               </seg>
         </p>
         <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter18_div4_div20_p18">
            <seg part="F" xml:id="C25_app599-f1818__F">
               </seg> With this resolution I traversed the  <seg xml:id="C25_app601-f1818">northern highlands,</seg> and fixed on one of the  <seg xml:id="C25_app603-f1818">remotest of the Orkneys as</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C25_app604-f1818">the scene labours.</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C25_app605-f1818">It was a place fitted for such</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C25_app606-f1818">a</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C25_app607-f1818">work,</seg> being hardly more than a  <seg xml:id="C25_app609-f1818">rock,</seg> whose high sides were continually beaten upon by the  <seg xml:id="C25_app611-f1818">waves.</seg> The soil was  <seg xml:id="C25_app613-f1818">barren, scarcely</seg> affording pasture for a few miserable  <seg xml:id="C25_app615-f1818">cows,</seg> and  <seg xml:id="C25_app617-f1818">oatmeal</seg> for its  <seg xml:id="C25_app619-f1818">inhabitants,</seg> which consisted of five  <seg xml:id="C25_app621-f1818">persons,</seg> whose gaunt and scraggy limbs gave  <seg xml:id="C25_app623-f1818">tokens</seg> of their  <seg xml:id="C25_app625-f1818">miserable</seg> fare.  <seg xml:id="C25_app627-f1818">Vegetables and bread, when they indulged in such luxuries, and even fresh</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C25_app628-f1818">water,</seg> was to be procured from the main  <seg xml:id="C25_app630-f1818">land,</seg> which was about five miles distant.  <seg part="I" xml:id="C25_app632-f1818__I">
               </seg>
         </p>
         <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter18_div4_div20_p19">
            <seg part="F" xml:id="C25_app632-f1818__F">
               </seg> On the whole island there were but <pb xml:id="F1818_v3_040" n="036"/>three miserable <seg xml:id="C25_app634-f1818">huts,</seg> and one of these was vacant when I arrived. This I  <seg xml:id="C25_app636-f1818">hired.</seg> It contained but two  <seg xml:id="C25_app638-f1818">rooms,</seg> and  <seg xml:id="C25_app640-f1818">these exhibited all the squalidness of the most miserable</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C25_app641-f1818">penury.</seg> The thatch had fallen  <seg xml:id="C25_app643-f1818">in,</seg> the walls were  <seg xml:id="C25_app645-f1818">unplastered,</seg> and the door was off its hinges. I ordered it to be repaired,  <seg xml:id="C25_app647-f1818">bought some</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C25_app648-f1818">furniture,</seg> and took  <seg xml:id="C25_app650-f1818">possession;</seg> an incident which  <seg xml:id="C25_app652-f1818">would, doubtless,</seg> have  <seg xml:id="C25_app654-f1818">occasioned some</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C25_app655-f1818">surprise,</seg> had not all the  <seg xml:id="C25_app657-f1818">senses of the cottagers been benumbed by want and squalid</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C25_app658-f1818">poverty.</seg> As it  <seg xml:id="C25_app660-f1818">was,</seg> I  <seg xml:id="C25_app662-f1818">lived ungazed at and unmolested, hardly thanked for the pittance of food and clothes which I</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C25_app663-f1818">gave;</seg> so much does suffering blunt even the coarsest sensations of men.  <seg part="I" xml:id="C25_app665-f1818__I">
               </seg>
         </p>
         <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter18_div4_div20_p20">
            <seg part="F" xml:id="C25_app665-f1818__F"> In this retreat I devoted the morning to</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C25_app666-f1818">labour;</seg> but in the evening, when the weather  <seg xml:id="C25_app668-f1818">permitted,</seg> I walked on the stony beach of the  <seg xml:id="C25_app670-f1818">sea,</seg> to listen to the <pb xml:id="F1818_v3_041" n="037"/>waves as they <seg xml:id="C25_app672-f1818">roared,</seg> and dashed at my  <seg xml:id="C25_app674-f1818">feet.</seg> It was a  <seg xml:id="C25_app676-f1818">monotonous,</seg> yet  <seg xml:id="C25_app678-f1818">ever-changing</seg> scene. I thought of  <seg xml:id="C25_app680-f1818">Switzerland;</seg> it was far different from this desolate and appalling  <seg xml:id="C25_app682-f1818">landscape. Its</seg> hills are covered with  <seg xml:id="C25_app684-f1818">vines,</seg> and its cottages are scattered  <seg xml:id="C25_app686-f1818">thickly</seg> in the  <seg xml:id="C25_app688-f1818">plains.</seg> Its fair lakes reflect a blue and gentle  <seg xml:id="C25_app690-f1818">sky; and,</seg> when troubled by the  <seg xml:id="C25_app692-f1818">winds, their tumult</seg> is but  <seg xml:id="C25_app694-f1818">as</seg> the play of a lively  <seg xml:id="C25_app696-f1818">infant,</seg> when compared to the roarings of the giant ocean. </p>
         <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter18_div4_div20_p21"> In <seg xml:id="C25_app698-f1818">this</seg> manner I distributed my occupations when I first arrived;  <seg xml:id="C25_app700-f1818">but,</seg> as I proceeded in my   <seg xml:id="C25_app703-f1818">labour,</seg> it became every day more horrible and irksome to me. Sometimes I could  <seg xml:id="C25_app705-f1818">not prevail on myself to enter my</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C25_app706-f1818">laboratory</seg> for several   <seg xml:id="C25_app708-f1818">days;</seg> and at other times I  <seg xml:id="C25_app710-f1818">toiled</seg> day   <seg xml:id="C25_app712-f1818">and night</seg> in order to  <seg xml:id="C25_app714-f1818">complete</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C25_app715-f1818">my work.</seg> It  <seg xml:id="C25_app717-f1818">was indeed</seg> a  <seg xml:id="C25_app719-f1818">filthy</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C25_app720-f1818">process</seg> in which I  <seg xml:id="C25_app722-f1818">was engaged.</seg> During <pb xml:id="F1818_v3_042" n="038"/>my first  <seg xml:id="C25_app725-f1818">experiment,</seg> a kind of enthusiastic frenzy  <seg xml:id="C25_app727-f1818">had</seg> blinded me to the horror of my employment; my mind was intently fixed on the   <seg xml:id="C25_app729-f1818">sequel</seg> of my  <seg xml:id="C25_app731-f1818">labour,</seg> and my eyes were shut to the horror of my proceedings. But now I went to it in cold  <seg xml:id="C25_app733-f1818">blood,</seg> and my heart often  <seg xml:id="C25_app735-f1818">sickened</seg> at the work of my hands. </p>
         <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter18_div4_div20_p22"> Thus <seg xml:id="C25_app737-f1818">situated,</seg> employed in the most detestable occupation,  <seg xml:id="C25_app739-f1818">immersed</seg> in  <seg xml:id="C25_app741-f1818">a</seg> solitude   <seg xml:id="C25_app743-f1818">where</seg> nothing could for an instant call my  <seg xml:id="C25_app745-f1818">attention</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C25_app746-f1818">from the actual scene in which I was engaged, my spirits</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C25_app747-f1818">became unequal;</seg> I  <seg xml:id="C25_app749-f1818">grew</seg> restless and  <seg xml:id="C25_app751-f1818">nervous.</seg> Every moment I feared to meet  <seg xml:id="C25_app753-f1818">my persecutor. Sometimes I sat with my eyes fixed on the</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C25_app754-f1818">ground,</seg> fearing to raise  <seg xml:id="C25_app756-f1818">them</seg> lest they should  <seg xml:id="C25_app758-f1818">encounter</seg> the object which I so much dreaded to   <seg xml:id="C25_app761-f1818">behold.</seg> I feared to wander from the sight of my  <seg xml:id="C25_app763-f1818">fellow-creatures,</seg>
            <pb xml:id="F1818_v3_043" n="039"/>lest when alone <seg xml:id="C25_app765-f1818">he should come to claim his companion.</seg>
            <seg part="I" xml:id="C25_app766-f1818__I">
               </seg>
         </p>
         <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter18_div4_div20_p23">
            <seg part="F" xml:id="C25_app766-f1818__F">
               </seg> In the mean time I worked  <seg xml:id="C25_app768-f1818">on,</seg> and my  <seg xml:id="C25_app770-f1818">labour was already considerably</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C25_app771-f1818">advanced.</seg> I looked  <seg xml:id="C25_app773-f1818">towards</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C25_app774-f1818">its</seg> completion   <seg xml:id="C25_app776-f1818">with a tremulous and eager hope, which</seg> I  <seg xml:id="C25_app778-f1818">dared not trust myself to question, but which</seg> was  <seg part="I" xml:id="C25_app780-f1818__I">intermixed with obscure forebodings of evil, that made my heart sicken in my bosom. </seg>
         </p>
         <seg part="F" xml:id="C25_app780-f1818__F">
            <milestone unit="chapter" type="end" n="18"/>
         </seg>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
