<?xml version="1.1" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
      xmlns:fv="https://frankensteinvariorum.github.io"
      xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Bridge Phase 6: f1831 chapter xviii</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Frankenstein Variorum Project</authority>
            <date>2023—</date>
            <availability>
               <licence>Distributed under a Creative Commons
                                                  Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported
                                                  License</licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Produced from a corpus of collation output files for
                                                the Frankenstein Variorum digital edition on
                                                  2023-07-10T15:38:58.3290983-04:00.</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <anchor type="semantic" subtype="start" xml:id="f1831_chapter_xviii"/>
         <milestone unit="chapter" type="start" n="18"/>
         <seg part="I" xml:id="C24_app2-f1831__I">
            <head ana="start"/>CHAPTER XVIII.<head ana="end"/>
         </seg>
         <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter18_div4_div18_p1">
            <seg part="F" xml:id="C24_app2-f1831__F">D<hi xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter18_div4_div18_p1_hi1">AY</hi>
            </seg> after day, week after  <seg xml:id="C24_app4-f1831">week,</seg> passed away on my return to   <seg xml:id="C24_app7-f1831">Geneva;</seg> and I  <seg xml:id="C24_app9-f1831">could</seg> not  <seg xml:id="C24_app11-f1831">collect</seg> the courage to  <seg xml:id="C24_app13-f1831">recommence</seg> my work.  <seg xml:id="C24_app15-f1831">I feared the vengeance of the disappointed fiend, yet I was unable to overcome my repugnance to the task which was enjoined me. I found that I could not compose a female without again devoting several months to profound study and laborious disquisition. I had heard of some discoveries having been made by an English philosopher, the knowledge of which was material to my success, and I sometimes thought of obtaining my father’s consent to visit England for this purpose; but I clung to every pretence of delay, and shrunk from taking the first step in an undertaking whose immediate necessity began to appear less absolute to me. A change indeed had taken place in me: my health, which had hitherto declined, was now much restored;</seg> and my  <seg xml:id="C24_app17-f1831">spirits,</seg> when unchecked by the memory of my unhappy promise, rose  <seg xml:id="C24_app19-f1831">proportionably.</seg> My father saw this  <seg xml:id="C24_app21-f1831">change</seg> with  <seg xml:id="C24_app23-f1831">pleasure,</seg> and he turned his thoughts towards the best  <seg xml:id="C24_app25-f1831">method</seg> of eradicating the remains of my  <seg xml:id="C24_app27-f1831">melancholy,</seg> which every now and then would return by  <seg xml:id="C24_app29-f1831">fits,</seg> and with a devouring blackness overcast the approaching  <seg xml:id="C24_app31-f1831">sunshine.</seg> At these moments I took refuge in the most perfect  <seg xml:id="C24_app33-f1831">solitude. I passed whole days on the lake alone in a little boat,</seg> watching the  <seg xml:id="C24_app35-f1831">clouds,</seg> and listening to  the   <seg xml:id="C24_app39-f1831">rippling</seg> of the waves, silent and listless. But the fresh air and bright sun seldom failed to restore me to some degree <pb xml:id="F1831_v_148" n="132"/>of <seg xml:id="C24_app41-f1831">composure; and,</seg> on my  <seg xml:id="C24_app43-f1831">return,</seg> I met the  <seg xml:id="C24_app45-f1831">salutations of my friends with a readier</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C24_app46-f1831">smile</seg> and a  more cheerful   <seg part="I" xml:id="C24_app50-f1831__I">heart. </seg>
         </p>
         <seg part="F" xml:id="C24_app50-f1831__F">
            </seg>
         <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter18_div4_div18_p2"> It was after my return from one of <seg xml:id="C24_app52-f1831">these</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C24_app53-f1831">rambles,</seg> that my  <seg xml:id="C24_app55-f1831">father,</seg> calling me  <seg xml:id="C24_app57-f1831">aside,</seg> thus  <seg xml:id="C24_app59-f1831">addressed me:—</seg>
         </p>
         <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter18_div4_div18_p3">
            <seg xml:id="C24_app61-f1831">“I</seg> am happy to remark, my dear son, that  <seg xml:id="C24_app63-f1831">you have</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C24_app64-f1831">resumed your former</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C24_app65-f1831">pleasures,</seg> and seem to be returning to yourself. And yet  <seg xml:id="C24_app67-f1831">you are still</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C24_app68-f1831">unhappy,</seg> and still avoid our society.  <seg part="I" xml:id="C24_app70-f1831__I">For some time I was lost in conjecture as to the cause of this; but yesterday an idea struck me, and if it is well founded, I conjure you to avow it. Reserve on such a point would be not only useless, but draw down treble misery on us all.” </seg>
         </p>
         <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter18_div4_div18_p4">
            <seg part="F" xml:id="C24_app70-f1831__F"> I trembled violently at</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C24_app71-f1831">his</seg>
            <seg part="I" xml:id="C24_app72-f1831__I">exordium, and my father continued— </seg>
         </p>
         <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter18_div4_div18_p5">
            <seg part="F" xml:id="C24_app72-f1831__F"> “I confess, my son, that I have always looked forward to your marriage with</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C24_app73-f1831">our dear Elizabeth</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C24_app74-f1831">as the tie of our domestic comfort, and the stay of my declining years. You were attached to each other from your earliest infancy; you studied together, and appeared, in dispositions and tastes, entirely suited to one another. But so blind is the experience of man, that what I conceived to be the best assistants to my</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C24_app75-f1831">plan,</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C24_app76-f1831">may have entirely destroyed it. You, perhaps, regard her as your sister, without any wish that she might become your wife. Nay, you may have met with another whom you may love; and, considering yourself as bound in honour to</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C24_app77-f1831">Elizabeth,</seg>
            <seg part="I" xml:id="C24_app78-f1831__I">this struggle may occasion the poignant misery which you appear to feel.” </seg>
         </p>
         <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter18_div4_div18_p6">
            <seg part="F" xml:id="C24_app78-f1831__F"> “My dear father, re-assure yourself. I love my cousin tenderly and sincerely. I never saw any</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C24_app79-f1831">woman</seg>
            <seg part="I" xml:id="C24_app80-f1831__I">who excited, as Elizabeth does, my warmest admiration and affection. My future hopes and prospects are entirely bound up in the expectation of our union.” </seg>
         </p>
         <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter18_div4_div18_p7">
            <seg part="F" xml:id="C24_app80-f1831__F"> “The expression of your sentiments on this subject, my dear Victor, gives me more pleasure than I have</seg> for some time  <seg xml:id="C24_app82-f1831">experienced. If you feel thus, we shall assuredly be happy, however present events may cast a gloom over us.</seg> But it is this  <seg xml:id="C24_app84-f1831">gloom</seg> which appears to have taken  <seg xml:id="C24_app86-f1831">so</seg> strong a hold of your  <seg xml:id="C24_app88-f1831">mind,</seg> that I wish to  <seg xml:id="C24_app90-f1831">dissipate.</seg> Tell  <seg xml:id="C24_app92-f1831">me, therefore,</seg> whether you object to an immediate  <seg xml:id="C24_app94-f1831">solemnisation</seg> of the marriage. We have been  <seg xml:id="C24_app96-f1831">unfortunate,</seg> and <pb xml:id="F1831_v_149" n="133"/>recent events have drawn us from that <seg xml:id="C24_app98-f1831">every-day</seg> tranquillity  <seg xml:id="C24_app100-f1831">befitting my years and infirmities. You are</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C24_app101-f1831">younger;</seg> yet I do not suppose, possessed as you are of a competent  <seg xml:id="C24_app103-f1831">fortune,</seg> that an early marriage would at all interfere with any future plans of honour and utility  <seg xml:id="C24_app105-f1831">that you may have</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C24_app106-f1831">formed.</seg> Do not  <seg xml:id="C24_app108-f1831">suppose, however,</seg> that I wish to dictate happiness to  <seg xml:id="C24_app110-f1831">you,</seg> or that a delay on your part would cause me any  <seg xml:id="C24_app112-f1831">serious</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C24_app113-f1831">uneasiness. Interpret</seg> my words with  <seg xml:id="C24_app115-f1831">candour,</seg> and answer  <seg xml:id="C24_app117-f1831">me,</seg> I conjure  <seg xml:id="C24_app119-f1831">you,</seg> with confidence and  <seg xml:id="C24_app121-f1831">sincerity.”</seg>
         </p>
         <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter18_div4_div18_p8"> I listened to my father in <seg xml:id="C24_app123-f1831">silence,</seg> and remained  <seg xml:id="C24_app125-f1831">for</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C24_app126-f1831">some time incapable of</seg> offering any reply. I revolved rapidly in my mind a multitude of  <seg xml:id="C24_app128-f1831">thoughts,</seg> and  <seg xml:id="C24_app130-f1831">endeavoured to</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C24_app131-f1831">arrive at</seg> some conclusion. Alas! to me the idea of an immediate union with my  <seg xml:id="C24_app133-f1831">Elizabeth</seg> was one of horror and dismay. I was bound by a solemn  <seg xml:id="C24_app135-f1831">promise,</seg> which I had not yet  <seg xml:id="C24_app137-f1831">fulfilled,</seg> and dared not break;  <seg xml:id="C24_app139-f1831">or,</seg> if I  <seg xml:id="C24_app141-f1831">did,</seg> what manifold miseries might not impend over me and  <seg xml:id="C24_app143-f1831">my devoted</seg> family!  <seg xml:id="C24_app145-f1831">Could I enter into a festival with this deadly weight yet hanging round my</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C24_app146-f1831">neck,</seg> and bowing me to the ground.  <seg xml:id="C24_app148-f1831">I must</seg> perform my   <seg xml:id="C24_app150-f1831">engagement,</seg> and let the monster depart with his  <seg xml:id="C24_app152-f1831">mate,</seg> before I allowed myself to enjoy the delight of  <seg xml:id="C24_app154-f1831">an union</seg> from which I expected  <seg part="I" xml:id="C24_app156-f1831__I">peace. </seg>
         </p>
         <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter18_div4_div18_p9">
            <seg part="F" xml:id="C24_app156-f1831__F">
               </seg> I  <seg xml:id="C24_app158-f1831">remembered</seg> also the necessity  <seg xml:id="C24_app160-f1831">imposed upon me</seg> of either  <seg xml:id="C24_app162-f1831">journeying</seg> to   <seg xml:id="C24_app164-f1831">England,</seg> or entering into a long correspondence with  <seg xml:id="C24_app166-f1831">those</seg> philosophers of that   <seg xml:id="C24_app169-f1831">country,</seg> whose knowledge and discoveries  <seg xml:id="C24_app171-f1831">were</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C24_app172-f1831">of</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C24_app173-f1831">indispensable</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C24_app174-f1831">use</seg> to me  <seg xml:id="C24_app176-f1831">in my present</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C24_app177-f1831">undertaking.</seg> The latter method of obtaining the desired intelligence was dilatory and  <seg xml:id="C24_app179-f1831">unsatisfactory: besides,</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C24_app180-f1831">I had an insurmountable aversion to the idea of engaging myself in my loathsome task in my father’s house, while in habits of familiar intercourse with those I loved. I knew that a thousand fearful accidents might occur, the slightest of which would disclose a tale to thrill all connected with me with horror. I was aware also that I should often lose all self-command, all capacity of hiding the harrowing sensations that would possess me during the progress of my unearthly occupation. I must absent myself from all I loved while thus employed. Once <pb xml:id="F1831_v_150" n="134"/>commenced, it would quickly be achieved, and I might be restored to</seg> my  <seg xml:id="C24_app191-f1831">family</seg> in peace and  <seg xml:id="C24_app196-f1831">happiness.</seg> My promise fulfilled, the monster  <seg xml:id="C24_app202-f1831">would depart for ever.</seg> Or  <seg xml:id="C24_app204-f1831">(so my fond fancy imaged) some</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C24_app205-f1831">accident might</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C24_app206-f1831">meanwhile occur to destroy</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C24_app207-f1831">him,</seg> and put  <seg xml:id="C24_app209-f1831">an</seg> end to my slavery for  <seg part="I" xml:id="C24_app211-f1831__I">ever. </seg>
         </p>
         <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter18_div4_div18_p10">
            <seg part="F" xml:id="C24_app211-f1831__F"> These</seg> feelings dictated my answer to my father. I  <seg xml:id="C24_app213-f1831">expressed</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C24_app214-f1831">a</seg> wish   <seg xml:id="C24_app216-f1831">to visit</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C24_app217-f1831">England; but,</seg> concealing  <seg xml:id="C24_app219-f1831">the</seg> true reasons   <seg xml:id="C24_app221-f1831">of this</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C24_app222-f1831">request,</seg> I clothed my desires under  <seg part="I" xml:id="C24_app224-f1831__I">a guise which excited no suspicion, while I urged my desire with an earnestness that easily induced my father to comply. After so long a period of an absorbing melancholy, that resembled madness in its intensity and effects, he was glad to find that I was capable of taking pleasure in the idea of such a journey, and he hoped that change of scene and varied amusement would, before my return, have restored me entirely to myself.</seg>
         </p>
         <seg part="M" xml:id="C24_app224-f1831__M">
            <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter18_div4_div18_p11">The duration of my absence was left to my own choice; a few months, or at most a year, was the period contemplated. One paternal kind precaution he had taken to ensure my having a companion. Without previously communicating with me, he had, in concert with Elizabeth, arranged that Clerval should join me at Strasburgh. This interfered with the solitude I coveted for the prosecution of my task; yet at the commencement of my journey the presence of my friend could in no way be an impediment, and truly I rejoiced that thus I should be saved many hours of lonely, maddening reflection. Nay, Henry might stand between me and the intrusion of my foe. If I were alone, would he not at times force his abhorred presence on me, to remind me of my task, or to contemplate its progress?</p>
         </seg>
         <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter18_div4_div18_p12">
            <seg part="F" xml:id="C24_app224-f1831__F">To England, therefore, I was bound, and it was understood that my union with Elizabeth should take place immediately on my return. My father’s age rendered him extremely averse to delay. For myself, there was one reward I promised myself from my detested toils—one consolation for my unparalleled sufferings; it was the prospect of that day when, enfranchised from my miserable slavery, I might claim Elizabeth, and forget the past in my union with her.</seg>
         </p>
         <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter18_div4_div18_p13"> I now <seg xml:id="C24_app294-f1831">made arrangements</seg> for my   <seg xml:id="C24_app296-f1831">journey;</seg> but one <pb xml:id="F1831_v_151" n="135"/>feeling haunted <seg xml:id="C24_app298-f1831">me,</seg> which filled  <seg xml:id="C24_app300-f1831">me with fear and agitation. During my absence I should leave my friends unconscious of the existence of their enemy, and unprotected from his attacks,</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C24_app301-f1831">exasperated as he might be by my departure. But he had promised to follow me wherever I might</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C24_app302-f1831">go;</seg> and would he not accompany me to England? This  <seg xml:id="C24_app304-f1831">imagination</seg> was dreadful in   <seg xml:id="C24_app306-f1831">itself,</seg> but  <seg xml:id="C24_app308-f1831">soothing, inasmuch</seg> as  <seg xml:id="C24_app310-f1831">it supposed the safety of</seg> my   <seg xml:id="C24_app312-f1831">friends.</seg> I was  <seg xml:id="C24_app314-f1831">agonised</seg> with  <seg xml:id="C24_app316-f1831">the idea of</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C24_app317-f1831">the</seg> possibility that the reverse of this might happen.  <seg xml:id="C24_app319-f1831">But</seg> through the whole period during which I was the slave of my  <seg xml:id="C24_app321-f1831">creature,</seg> I allowed myself to be  <seg xml:id="C24_app323-f1831">governed by</seg> the impulses of the  <seg xml:id="C24_app325-f1831">moment;</seg> and my  <seg xml:id="C24_app327-f1831">present sensations strongly intimated</seg>
            <seg part="I" xml:id="C24_app328-f1831__I">that the fiend would follow me, and exempt my family from the danger of his machinations.</seg>
         </p>
         <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter18_div4_div18_p14">
            <seg part="F" xml:id="C24_app328-f1831__F">
               </seg>
            <seg xml:id="C24_app329-f1831">It was in the latter end of September that I again quitted my native country. My journey had been my own suggestion, and Elizabeth, therefore, acquiesced: but she was filled with disquiet at the idea of my suffering, away from her, the inroads of misery and grief. It had been her care which provided me a companion in Clerval—and yet a man is blind to a thousand minute circumstances, which call forth a woman’s sedulous attention. She longed to bid me hasten my return,—a thousand conflicting emotions rendered her mute, as she bade me a tearful silent farewell.</seg>
            <seg part="I" xml:id="C24_app330-f1831__I">
               </seg>
         </p>
         <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter18_div4_div18_p15">
            <seg part="F" xml:id="C24_app330-f1831__F"> I threw myself into the carriage that was to convey me away, hardly knowing whither I was going, and careless of what was passing around. I remembered only, and it was with a bitter anguish that I reflected on it, to order that my chemical instruments should be packed to go with</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C24_app331-f1831">me.</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C24_app332-f1831">Filled with dreary imaginations, I passed through</seg> many beautiful and majestic  <seg xml:id="C24_app334-f1831">scenes;</seg> but my eyes were fixed and  <seg xml:id="C24_app336-f1831">unobserving.</seg> I  <seg xml:id="C24_app338-f1831">could only</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C24_app339-f1831">think</seg> of the bourne of my  <seg xml:id="C24_app341-f1831">travels,</seg> and the work which was to occupy me whilst they endured.  <seg part="I" xml:id="C24_app343-f1831__I">
               </seg>
         </p>
         <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter18_div4_div18_p16">
            <seg part="F" xml:id="C24_app343-f1831__F">
               </seg> After some days  <seg xml:id="C24_app345-f1831">spent</seg> in listless  <seg xml:id="C24_app347-f1831">indolence,</seg> during which I  <seg xml:id="C24_app349-f1831">traversed many</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C24_app350-f1831">leagues,</seg> I arrived at  <seg xml:id="C24_app352-f1831">Strasburgh,</seg> where I waited two days for Clerval. He  <seg xml:id="C24_app354-f1831">came.</seg> Alas, how great was the contrast between  <seg xml:id="C24_app356-f1831">us!</seg> He was alive to every new scene; joyful when he saw the beauties of  <seg xml:id="C24_app358-f1831">the</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C24_app359-f1831">setting sun,</seg>
            <pb xml:id="F1831_v_152" n="136"/>and more happy when he <seg xml:id="C24_app361-f1831">beheld</seg> it  <seg xml:id="C24_app363-f1831">rise, and recommence</seg> a new day. He pointed out to me the shifting colours  <seg xml:id="C24_app365-f1831">of the</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C24_app366-f1831">landscape,</seg> and the appearances of the sky.  <seg xml:id="C24_app368-f1831">“This</seg> is what it is to  <seg xml:id="C24_app370-f1831">live,”</seg> he cried,  <seg xml:id="C24_app372-f1831">“now</seg> I enjoy  <seg xml:id="C24_app374-f1831">existence!</seg> But you, my dear Frankenstein,  <seg xml:id="C24_app376-f1831">wherefore are you</seg> desponding   <seg xml:id="C24_app378-f1831">and</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C24_app379-f1831">sorrowful!”</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C24_app380-f1831">In truth,</seg> I was occupied by gloomy  <seg xml:id="C24_app382-f1831">thoughts,</seg> and neither saw the  <seg xml:id="C24_app384-f1831">descent</seg> of the evening   <seg xml:id="C24_app386-f1831">star,</seg> nor the golden  <seg xml:id="C24_app388-f1831">sunrise</seg> reflected in the  <seg xml:id="C24_app390-f1831">Rhine.—And</seg> you, my friend, would be far more amused with the journal of  <seg xml:id="C24_app392-f1831">Clerval,</seg> who observed the scenery with an eye of feeling and delight, than  <seg xml:id="C24_app394-f1831">in listening</seg> to my  <seg xml:id="C24_app396-f1831">reflections.</seg> I, a miserable  <seg xml:id="C24_app398-f1831">wretch,</seg> haunted by a curse that shut up every avenue to enjoyment. </p>
         <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter18_div4_div18_p17"> We had agreed to <seg xml:id="C24_app400-f1831">descend</seg> the Rhine in a boat from  <seg xml:id="C24_app402-f1831">Strasburgh</seg> to  <seg xml:id="C24_app404-f1831">Rotterdam,</seg> whence we might take shipping for London. During this  <seg xml:id="C24_app406-f1831">voyage,</seg> we passed many willowy  <seg xml:id="C24_app410-f1831">islands,</seg> and saw several beautiful towns. We  <seg xml:id="C24_app412-f1831">stayed</seg> a day at Manheim,  <seg xml:id="C24_app414-f1831">and,</seg> on the fifth from our departure from  <seg xml:id="C24_app416-f1831">Strasburgh,</seg> arrived at Mayence. The course of the Rhine below Mayence becomes much more picturesque. The river descends  <seg xml:id="C24_app418-f1831">rapidly,</seg> and winds between  <seg xml:id="C24_app420-f1831">hills,</seg> not  <seg xml:id="C24_app422-f1831">high,</seg> but  <seg xml:id="C24_app424-f1831">steep,</seg> and of beautiful forms. We saw many ruined  <seg xml:id="C24_app426-f1831">castles</seg> standing on the edges  <seg xml:id="C24_app428-f1831">of</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C24_app429-f1831">precipices,</seg> surrounded by black  <seg xml:id="C24_app431-f1831">woods,</seg> high and inaccessible. This part of the  <seg xml:id="C24_app433-f1831">Rhine, indeed,</seg> presents a  <seg xml:id="C24_app435-f1831">singularly variegated</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C24_app436-f1831">landscape.</seg> In one spot you view rugged hills, ruined   <seg xml:id="C24_app439-f1831">castles</seg> overlooking tremendous  <seg xml:id="C24_app441-f1831">precipices,</seg> with the dark Rhine rushing  <seg xml:id="C24_app443-f1831">beneath; and,</seg> on the sudden turn of a  <seg xml:id="C24_app445-f1831">promontory,</seg> flourishing  <seg xml:id="C24_app447-f1831">vineyards,</seg> with green sloping  <seg xml:id="C24_app449-f1831">banks,</seg> and a meandering  <seg xml:id="C24_app451-f1831">river, and populous</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C24_app452-f1831">towns</seg> occupy the scene.  <seg part="I" xml:id="C24_app454-f1831__I">
               </seg>
         </p>
         <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter18_div4_div18_p18">
            <seg part="F" xml:id="C24_app454-f1831__F">
               </seg> We travelled at the time of the  <seg xml:id="C24_app456-f1831">vintage,</seg> and heard the song of the  <seg xml:id="C24_app458-f1831">labourers,</seg> as we glided down the stream. Even I, depressed in  <seg xml:id="C24_app460-f1831">mind,</seg> and my spirits continually agitated by gloomy  <seg xml:id="C24_app462-f1831">feelings,</seg> even I was pleased. I lay at the bottom of the  <seg xml:id="C24_app464-f1831">boat, and,</seg> as I gazed on the cloudless blue  <seg xml:id="C24_app466-f1831">sky,</seg> I  <seg xml:id="C24_app468-f1831">seemed to</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C24_app469-f1831">drink</seg> in a tranquillity to which I had long been a stranger. And if these were my  <seg xml:id="C24_app471-f1831">sensations,</seg> who can describe those of  <seg xml:id="C24_app473-f1831">Henry?</seg> He felt as if he had been transported to  <seg xml:id="C24_app475-f1831">Fairy-land,</seg> and enjoyed a happiness seldom tasted by man.  <seg xml:id="C24_app477-f1831">“I</seg> have  <seg xml:id="C24_app479-f1831">seen,”</seg> he said,  <seg xml:id="C24_app481-f1831">“the</seg> most beautiful <pb xml:id="F1831_v_153" n="137"/>scenes of my own <seg xml:id="C24_app483-f1831">country;</seg> I have  <seg xml:id="C24_app485-f1831">visited</seg> the lakes of Lucerne and  <seg xml:id="C24_app487-f1831">Uri,</seg> where the snowy mountains descend almost perpendicularly to the  <seg xml:id="C24_app489-f1831">water,</seg> casting black and impenetrable  <seg xml:id="C24_app491-f1831">shades,</seg> which  <seg xml:id="C24_app493-f1831">would cause</seg> a gloomy and mournful   <seg xml:id="C24_app495-f1831">appearance,</seg> were it not for the most verdant islands that relieve the eye by their gay  <seg xml:id="C24_app497-f1831">appearance;</seg> I have seen this lake agitated by a  <seg xml:id="C24_app499-f1831">tempest,</seg> when the wind tore up whirlwinds of  <seg xml:id="C24_app501-f1831">water,</seg> and gave you an idea of what the  <seg xml:id="C24_app503-f1831">water-spout</seg> must be on the great  <seg xml:id="C24_app505-f1831">ocean; and</seg> the waves dash with fury  <seg xml:id="C24_app507-f1831">the</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C24_app508-f1831">base of the</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C24_app509-f1831">mountain,</seg> where the priest and his mistress were overwhelmed by an  <seg xml:id="C24_app511-f1831">avalanche,</seg> and where their dying voices are still said to be heard amid the pauses of the  <seg xml:id="C24_app513-f1831">nightly wind;</seg> I have seen the  <seg xml:id="C24_app515-f1831">mountains of La</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C24_app516-f1831">Valais,</seg> and the Pays de  <seg xml:id="C24_app518-f1831">Vaud:</seg> but this country, Victor, pleases me more than all those wonders. The mountains of Switzerland are more majestic and  <seg xml:id="C24_app520-f1831">strange;</seg> but there is a charm in the banks of this divine  <seg xml:id="C24_app522-f1831">river,</seg> that I never before saw equalled. Look at that castle which overhangs  <seg xml:id="C24_app524-f1831">yon</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C24_app525-f1831">precipice;</seg> and that also on the  <seg xml:id="C24_app527-f1831">island,</seg> almost concealed  <seg xml:id="C24_app529-f1831">amongst</seg> the foliage of those lovely  <seg xml:id="C24_app531-f1831">trees; and</seg> now that group of  <seg xml:id="C24_app533-f1831">labourers</seg> coming from among their vines; and that village  <seg xml:id="C24_app535-f1831">half hid</seg> in the recess of the mountain.  <seg xml:id="C24_app537-f1831">Oh, surely,</seg> the spirit that inhabits and guards this place has a soul more in  <seg xml:id="C24_app539-f1831">harmony</seg> with   <seg xml:id="C24_app541-f1831">man,</seg> than those who pile the  <seg xml:id="C24_app543-f1831">glacier,</seg> or retire to the inaccessible peaks of the mountains of our own  <seg part="I" xml:id="C24_app545-f1831__I">country.” </seg>
         </p>
         <seg part="F" xml:id="C24_app545-f1831__F">
            </seg>
         <seg part="I" xml:id="C24_app546-f1831__I">
            </seg>
         <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter18_div4_div18_p19">
            <seg part="F" xml:id="C24_app546-f1831__F">Clerval! beloved friend! even now it delights me to record your words, and to dwell on the praise of which you are so eminently deserving. He was a being formed in the <quote xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter18_div4_div18_p19_quote1">“very poetry of nature.”</quote> His wild and enthusiastic imagination was chastened by the sensibility of his heart. His soul overflowed with ardent affections, and his friendship was of that devoted and wondrous nature that the worldly-minded teach us to look for only in the imagination. But even human sympathies were not sufficient to satisfy his eager mind. The scenery of external nature, which others regard only with admiration, he loved with ardour:— <pb xml:id="F1831_v_154" n="138"/>
            </seg>
            <seg part="I" xml:id="C24_app547-f1831__I">
               </seg>
            <cit xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter18_div4_div18_p19_cit1">
               <quote xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter18_div4_div18_p19_cit1_quote1">
                  <lg xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter18_div4_div18_p19_cit1_quote1_lg1">
                     <seg part="M" xml:id="C24_app547-f1831__M">
                        <l xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter18_div4_div18_p19_cit1_quote1_lg1_l1"> ————————————“The sounding cataract </l>
                        <l xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter18_div4_div18_p19_cit1_quote1_lg1_l2"> Haunted him like a passion: the tall rock, </l>
                        <l xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter18_div4_div18_p19_cit1_quote1_lg1_l3"> The mountain, and the deep and gloomy wood, </l>
                        <l xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter18_div4_div18_p19_cit1_quote1_lg1_l4"> Their colours and their forms, were then to him </l>
                        <l xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter18_div4_div18_p19_cit1_quote1_lg1_l5"> An appetite; a feeling, and a love, </l>
                        <l xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter18_div4_div18_p19_cit1_quote1_lg1_l6"> That had no need of a remoter charm, </l>
                        <l xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter18_div4_div18_p19_cit1_quote1_lg1_l7"> By thought supplied, or any interest </l>
                     </seg>
                     <l xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter18_div4_div18_p19_cit1_quote1_lg1_l8">
                        <seg part="F" xml:id="C24_app547-f1831__F">
                           </seg>
                        <seg xml:id="C24_app548-f1831">Unborrow’d</seg>
                        <seg part="I" xml:id="C24_app549-f1831__I">from the eye*.” </seg>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
               <note xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter18_div4_div18_p19_cit1_note1"> * <bibl xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter18_div4_div18_p19_cit1_note1_bibl1">
                     <seg part="F" xml:id="C24_app549-f1831__F"> Wordsworth’s</seg>
                     <seg xml:id="C24_app550-f1831">Tintern Abbey.</seg>
                     <seg part="I" xml:id="C24_app551-f1831__I">
                        </seg>
                  </bibl>
               </note>
            </cit>
         </p>
         <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter18_div4_div18_p20">
            <seg part="F" xml:id="C24_app551-f1831__F"> And where does he now exist? Is this gentle and lovely being lost</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C24_app552-f1831">for ever?</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C24_app553-f1831">Has this</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C24_app554-f1831">mind,</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C24_app555-f1831">so replete with ideas, imaginations fanciful and magnificent, which formed a world, whose existence depended on the life of its</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C24_app556-f1831">creator;—has</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C24_app557-f1831">this mind perished? Does it now only exist in my memory? No, it is not thus; your form so divinely wrought, and beaming with beauty, has decayed, but your spirit still visits and consoles your unhappy friend.</seg>
         </p>
         <seg xml:id="C24_app559-f1831">
            <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter18_div4_div18_p21"> Pardon this gush of sorrow; these ineffectual words are but a slight tribute to the unexampled worth of Henry, but they soothe my heart, overflowing with the anguish which his remembrance creates. I will proceed with my tale. </p>
         </seg>
         <seg xml:id="C25_app1-f1831">
            <anchor type="collate" xml:id="C25"/>
         </seg>
         <seg part="I" xml:id="C25_app2-f1831__I">
            </seg>
         <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter18_div4_div18_p22">
            <seg part="F" xml:id="C25_app2-f1831__F"> Beyond Cologne we descended to the plains of Holland;</seg> and we resolved to post the remainder of our  <seg xml:id="C25_app4-f1831">way;</seg> for the wind was  <seg xml:id="C25_app6-f1831">contrary,</seg> and the stream of the river was too gentle to aid us.  <seg part="I" xml:id="C25_app8-f1831__I">
               </seg>
         </p>
         <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter18_div4_div18_p23">
            <seg part="F" xml:id="C25_app8-f1831__F"> Our journey here lost the interest arising</seg> from  <seg xml:id="C25_app10-f1831">beautiful scenery; but we arrived in a few days at Rotterdam, whence</seg> we  <seg xml:id="C25_app12-f1831">proceeded</seg> by sea to England. It was on a clear  <seg xml:id="C25_app14-f1831">morning,</seg> in the latter days of   <seg xml:id="C25_app17-f1831">December,</seg> that I first saw the white cliffs of Britain. The banks  <seg xml:id="C25_app19-f1831">of the</seg> Thames presented a new scene; they were   <seg xml:id="C25_app21-f1831">flat,</seg> but  <seg xml:id="C25_app23-f1831">fertile, and almost every town was marked by the remembrance of some story.</seg> We saw Tilbury  <seg xml:id="C25_app25-f1831">Fort, and remembered</seg> the Spanish armada; Gravesend, Woolwich,  <seg xml:id="C25_app27-f1831">and Greenwich,</seg> places which I had heard of even in my country.  <seg part="I" xml:id="C25_app29-f1831__I">
               </seg>
         </p>
         <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter18_div4_div18_p24">
            <seg part="F" xml:id="C25_app29-f1831__F">
               </seg> At length we saw the numerous steeples of  <seg xml:id="C25_app31-f1831">London, St. Paul’s towering</seg> above  <seg xml:id="C25_app33-f1831">all,</seg> and the Tower famed in English history.  <seg part="I" xml:id="C25_app35-f1831__I">
               </seg>
         </p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
