<?xml version="1.1" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
      xmlns:fv="https://frankensteinvariorum.github.io"
      xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Bridge Phase 6: </title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Frankenstein Variorum Project</authority>
            <date>2023—</date>
            <availability>
               <licence>Distributed under a Creative Commons
                                                  Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported
                                                  License</licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Produced from a corpus of collation output files for
                                                the Frankenstein Variorum digital edition on
                                                  2023-07-15T22:42:22.079808-04:00.</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <anchor type="semantic" subtype="start" xml:id="f1831_chapter_i"/>
         <milestone unit="chapter" type="start" n="1"/>
         <seg part="I" xml:id="C07_app3-f1831__I">
            <head ana="start"/>CHAPTER I.<head ana="end"/>
         </seg>
         <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter1_div4_div1_p1">
            <seg part="F" xml:id="C07_app3-f1831__F"> I <hi xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter1_div4_div1_p1_hi1">AM</hi> by birth a Genevese; and my family is one of the most distinguished of that republic. My ancestors had been for many years counsellors and syndics; and my father</seg> had  <seg xml:id="C07_app5-f1831">filled several public situations with honour and reputation. He was respected by all who knew</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C07_app6-f1831">him,</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C07_app7-f1831">for his integrity and indefatigable attention</seg> to  <seg xml:id="C07_app9-f1831">public business. He passed his younger days perpetually occupied by the affairs of his country;</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C07_app10-f1831">a variety of circumstances had prevented his marrying early, nor</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C07_app11-f1831">was</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C07_app12-f1831">it</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C07_app13-f1831">until the decline of life that he</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C07_app14-f1831">became a husband</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C07_app15-f1831">and</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C07_app17-f1831">the</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C07_app18-f1831">father of a family.</seg>
            <seg part="I" xml:id="C07_app19-f1831__I">
               </seg>
         </p>
         <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter1_div4_div1_p2">
            <seg part="F" xml:id="C07_app19-f1831__F"> As the circumstances of his marriage illustrate his character, I cannot refrain from relating them. One of his most intimate friends was a merchant, who, from a flourishing state, fell, through numerous mischances, into poverty. This man, whose name was Beaufort, was of a proud and unbending disposition, and could not bear to live in poverty and oblivion in the same country where he had formerly been distinguished for his rank and magni<pb xml:id="F1831_v_035" n="19"/>ficence. Having paid his debts, therefore, in the most honourable manner, he retreated with his daughter to the town of Lucerne, where he lived unknown and in wretchedness. My father loved Beaufort with the truest friendship, and was deeply grieved by his retreat in these unfortunate circumstances. He</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C07_app20-f1831">bitterly deplored</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C07_app21-f1831">the</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C07_app22-f1831">false pride which led his friend to a conduct so little worthy</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C07_app23-f1831">of</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C07_app24-f1831">the affection that united them. He lost no time in endeavouring</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C07_app25-f1831">to seek him</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C07_app26-f1831">out,</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C07_app27-f1831">with the hope of persuading</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C07_app28-f1831">him to begin the world again</seg> through  <seg part="I" xml:id="C07_app30-f1831__I">his credit and assistance. </seg>
         </p>
         <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter1_div4_div1_p3">
            <seg part="F" xml:id="C07_app30-f1831__F"> Beaufort had taken effectual measures to conceal himself; and it was ten months before my father discovered his abode. Overjoyed at this discovery, he hastened to the house, which was situated in a mean street, near the Reuss. But when he entered, misery and despair alone welcomed him. Beaufort had saved but a very small sum of money from the wreck of his fortunes; but it was sufficient to provide him with sustenance for some months, and in the mean time he hoped to procure some respectable employment in a merchant’s house. The interval</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C07_app31-f1831">was, consequently,</seg>
            <seg part="I" xml:id="C07_app32-f1831__I">spent in inaction; his grief only became more deep and rankling, when he had leisure for reflection; and at length it took so fast hold of his mind, that at the end of three months he lay on a bed of sickness, incapable of any exertion. </seg>
         </p>
         <seg part="M" xml:id="C07_app32-f1831__M">
            <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter1_div4_div1_p4"> His daughter attended him with the greatest tenderness; but she saw with despair that their little fund was rapidly decreasing, and that there was no other prospect of support. But Caroline Beaufort possessed a mind of an uncommon mould; and her courage rose to support her in her adversity. She procured plain work; she plaited straw; and by various means contrived to earn a pittance scarcely sufficient to support life. </p>
         </seg>
         <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter1_div4_div1_p5">
            <seg part="F" xml:id="C07_app32-f1831__F"> Several months passed in this manner. Her father grew worse; her time was more entirely occupied in attending him; her means of subsistence decreased; and in the tenth month her father died in her arms, leaving her an orphan and a beggar. This last blow overcame her; and she knelt by Beaufort’s coffin, weeping bitterly, when my father entered the chamber. He came like a protecting spirit to the <pb xml:id="F1831_v_036" n="20"/>poor girl, who committed herself to his</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C07_app33-f1831">care;</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C07_app34-f1831">and after the interment of his</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C07_app35-f1831">friend,</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C07_app36-f1831">he conducted her to Geneva, and placed</seg> her  <seg part="I" xml:id="C07_app38-f1831__I">under the protection of a relation. Two years after this event Caroline became his wife. </seg>
         </p>
         <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter1_div4_div1_p6">
            <seg part="F" xml:id="C07_app38-f1831__F">
               </seg>
            <seg xml:id="C07_app39-f1831">There was a considerable difference between the ages of</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C07_app40-f1831">my</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C07_app41-f1831">parents, but this circumstance seemed to unite them only closer in bonds of devoted affection. There was</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C07_app42-f1831">a</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C07_app43-f1831">sense of justice in my father’s upright mind, which rendered it necessary that he should approve highly to love strongly. Perhaps during former years</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C07_app44-f1831">he</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C07_app45-f1831">had suffered from the late-discovered unworthiness of one beloved, and</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C07_app46-f1831">so</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C07_app47-f1831">was disposed to set a greater value on tried worth.</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C07_app48-f1831">There</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C07_app49-f1831">was a show</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C07_app50-f1831">of</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C07_app51-f1831">gratitude and worship in his</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C07_app52-f1831">attachment to my mother, differing wholly from the doating fondness</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C07_app55-f1831">of</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C07_app56-f1831">age, for it was inspired by reverence for her virtues,</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C07_app57-f1831">and</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C07_app58-f1831">a desire</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C07_app59-f1831">to</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C07_app60-f1831">be the means of, in some degree, recompensing her for</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C07_app61-f1831">the</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C07_app62-f1831">sorrows she had endured, but which gave inexpressible grace to</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C07_app64-f1831">his</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C07_app65-f1831">behaviour to her. Every thing</seg> was  <seg xml:id="C07_app67-f1831">made to yield to her wishes and her convenience. He strove to shelter her, as a</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C07_app68-f1831">fair exotic is sheltered by</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C07_app69-f1831">the</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C07_app70-f1831">gardener, from every rougher wind, and to surround her with all that could tend to excite pleasurable emotion</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C07_app71-f1831">in</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C07_app72-f1831">her soft and benevolent mind. Her health,</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C07_app73-f1831">and</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C07_app74-f1831">even the tranquillity of her hitherto constant spirit, had been shaken by what she had gone through. During the</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C07_app75-f1831">two years that had elapsed previous</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C07_app76-f1831">to</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C07_app77-f1831">their marriage my father had gradually relinquished all his</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C07_app78-f1831">public functions; and immediately after their union they sought the pleasant climate of Italy, and the change of scene</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C07_app79-f1831">and</seg>
            <seg part="I" xml:id="C07_app80-f1831__I">interest attendant on a tour through that land of wonders, as a restorative for her weakened frame. </seg>
         </p>
         <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter1_div4_div1_p7">
            <seg part="F" xml:id="C07_app80-f1831__F"> From Italy they visited Germany</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C07_app81-f1831">and</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C07_app82-f1831">France. I,</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C07_app83-f1831">their</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C07_app84-f1831">eldest child,</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C07_app85-f1831">was</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C07_app86-f1831">born at Naples, and as</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C07_app87-f1831">an infant accompanied them in their rambles. I remained for several years their only child.</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C07_app88-f1831">Much as they were attached to each other, they seemed to draw inexhaustible stores of affection from a very mine of love to bestow them upon me. My mother’s tender caresses, and</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C07_app89-f1831">my</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C07_app90-f1831">father’s smile of benevolent pleasure while regarding me, are my first recollections.</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C07_app93-f1831">I was</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C07_app94-f1831">their plaything and their idol, and something better—<pb xml:id="F1831_v_037" n="21"/>their child, the innocent and helpless creature bestowed on them by Heaven,</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C07_app95-f1831">whom</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C07_app96-f1831">to bring up to good,</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C07_app97-f1831">and</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C07_app98-f1831">whose future lot it was</seg> in  <seg xml:id="C07_app100-f1831">their hands to direct to happiness or misery, according as they fulfilled their duties towards me. With this deep consciousness of what they owed towards the being to which they</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C07_app101-f1831">had</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C07_app102-f1831">given life, added to the active spirit of tenderness</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C07_app103-f1831">that</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C07_app104-f1831">animated both, it may be imagined that while during every hour of my infant life</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C07_app108-f1831">I</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C07_app109-f1831">received a lesson of patience, of charity,</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C07_app110-f1831">and</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C07_app111-f1831">of self-control, I was so guided by</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C07_app112-f1831">a</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C07_app113-f1831">silken cord, that all seemed but one train</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C07_app114-f1831">of</seg>
            <seg part="I" xml:id="C07_app115-f1831__I">enjoyment to me. </seg>
         </p>
         <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter1_div4_div1_p8">
            <seg part="F" xml:id="C07_app115-f1831__F"> For a long time I was their only care.</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C07_app116-f1831">My</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C07_app117-f1831">mother had much desire</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C07_app118-f1831">to</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C07_app119-f1831">have a daughter, but I continued their single offspring. When</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C07_app120-f1831">I</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C07_app121-f1831">was about five years old, while making an excursion beyond the frontiers of</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C07_app122-f1831">Italy, they passed a week on the</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C07_app123-f1831">shores of</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C07_app124-f1831">the</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C07_app125-f1831">Lake</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C07_app126-f1831">of</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C07_app127-f1831">Como. Their benevolent disposition often made them enter the cottages of the poor. This, to</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C07_app128-f1831">my</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C07_app129-f1831">mother,</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C07_app130-f1831">was more</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C07_app131-f1831">than a duty; it was a necessity, a passion,—remembering what she had suffered,</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C07_app132-f1831">and</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C07_app133-f1831">how she had been relieved,—for</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C07_app134-f1831">her</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C07_app135-f1831">to act in</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C07_app136-f1831">her</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C07_app137-f1831">turn the guardian angel</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C07_app139-f1831">to</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C07_app140-f1831">the afflicted. During one of their walks a poor cot in the foldings of a vale attracted their notice, as being singularly disconsolate, while</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C07_app141-f1831">the</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C07_app142-f1831">number</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C07_app143-f1831">of</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C07_app144-f1831">half-clothed children gathered about it, spoke of penury in its worst shape. One day, when my father had gone by himself</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C07_app145-f1831">to</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C07_app146-f1831">Milan, my mother, accompanied</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C07_app147-f1831">by</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C07_app148-f1831">me, visited this abode. She found a peasant</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C07_app149-f1831">and</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C07_app150-f1831">his wife, hard working, bent down by care and labour, distributing a scanty meal</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C07_app151-f1831">to</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C07_app152-f1831">five hungry babes. Among these there was one which attracted</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C07_app153-f1831">my mother</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C07_app154-f1831">far above all the rest.</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C07_app155-f1831">She</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C07_app156-f1831">appeared of a different stock.</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C07_app157-f1831">The</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C07_app158-f1831">four others were dark-eyed, hardy little vagrants; this</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C07_app159-f1831">child</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C07_app160-f1831">was thin, and very fair. Her hair was the brightest living gold, and, despite the poverty</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C07_app163-f1831">of</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C07_app164-f1831">her clothing, seemed to set a</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C07_app165-f1831">crown of distinction on her head. Her brow was clear</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C07_app166-f1831">and</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C07_app167-f1831">ample, her blue eyes cloudless,</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C07_app168-f1831">and</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C07_app169-f1831">her lips and the moulding of her face so expressive</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C07_app170-f1831">of</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C07_app171-f1831">sensibility and sweetness, that none could behold her without looking on her</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C07_app172-f1831">as</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C07_app173-f1831">of a distinct species,</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C07_app174-f1831">a</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C07_app175-f1831">being heaven-sent,</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C07_app176-f1831">and</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C07_app177-f1831">bearing a celestial stamp in all her features.</seg>
            <seg part="I" xml:id="C07_app178-f1831__I">
               </seg>
         </p>
         <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter1_div4_div1_p9">
            <seg part="F" xml:id="C07_app178-f1831__F">
               </seg>
            <seg xml:id="C07_app179-f1831">
               <pb xml:id="F1831_v_038" n="22"/>The peasant woman, perceiving that</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C07_app180-f1831">my</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C07_app181-f1831">mother fixed eyes of wonder and admiration on this lovely girl, eagerly communicated her history.</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C07_app184-f1831">She was</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C07_app185-f1831">not her child, but the daughter of</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C07_app188-f1831">a</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C07_app189-f1831">Milanese nobleman. Her mother</seg> was  <seg xml:id="C07_app191-f1831">a German,</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C07_app192-f1831">and</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C07_app193-f1831">had died on giving</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C07_app194-f1831">her</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C07_app195-f1831">birth. The infant had been placed with these good people to nurse: they</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C07_app196-f1831">were</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C07_app197-f1831">better off then. They had</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C07_app198-f1831">not</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C07_app199-f1831">been long married,</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C07_app200-f1831">and</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C07_app201-f1831">their eldest child was but just born. The father of their charge was one of those Italians nursed in the memory of the antique glory of Italy,—one among the <hi xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter1_div4_div1_p9_hi1">schiavi ognor frementi</hi>, who exerted himself to obtain the liberty of his country. He became the victim of its weakness. Whether he had died,</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C07_app202-f1831">or</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C07_app203-f1831">still lingered in the dungeons of Austria, was not known. His property was confiscated, his child became an orphan</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C07_app204-f1831">and</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C07_app205-f1831">a beggar. She continued with her</seg>
            <seg part="I" xml:id="C07_app206-f1831__I">foster parents, and bloomed in their rude abode, fairer than a garden rose among dark-leaved brambles. </seg>
         </p>
         <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter1_div4_div1_p10">
            <seg part="F" xml:id="C07_app206-f1831__F"> When my father returned from Milan, he found playing</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C07_app207-f1831">with</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C07_app208-f1831">me in the hall of our villa, a child fairer</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C07_app209-f1831">than</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C07_app210-f1831">pictured cherub—a creature who seemed</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C07_app211-f1831">to</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C07_app212-f1831">shed radiance from her looks, and whose form</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C07_app213-f1831">and</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C07_app214-f1831">motions were lighter than the chamois of the hills. The apparition</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C07_app215-f1831">was</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C07_app216-f1831">soon explained. With his permission</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C07_app217-f1831">my</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C07_app218-f1831">mother prevailed on her</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C07_app219-f1831">rustic guardians to yield their charge to her. They were fond</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C07_app220-f1831">of</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C07_app221-f1831">the sweet orphan.</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C07_app223-f1831">Her</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C07_app224-f1831">presence had seemed a blessing to them;</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C07_app227-f1831">but it</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C07_app228-f1831">would be unfair to her</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C07_app229-f1831">to keep</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C07_app230-f1831">her</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C07_app231-f1831">in poverty and want, when Providence afforded her such powerful protection. They consulted their village priest,</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C07_app232-f1831">and</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C07_app233-f1831">the result was, that Elizabeth Lavenza became the inmate of my parents’ house—my more than sister—the beautiful and adored companion</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C07_app234-f1831">of</seg>
            <seg part="I" xml:id="C07_app235-f1831__I">all my occupations and my pleasures. </seg>
         </p>
         <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter1_div4_div1_p11">
            <seg part="F" xml:id="C07_app235-f1831__F"> Every one loved Elizabeth.</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C07_app236-f1831">The</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C07_app237-f1831">passionate and almost reverential attachment with which all regarded her became,</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C07_app238-f1831">while I</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C07_app239-f1831">shared it, my pride and my delight. On the evening previous to her being brought to my home, my mother had said playfully,—“I have a pretty present for my Victor—to-morrow he shall have it.” And when, on the morrow, she presented Elizabeth to me as her promised gift, I, with childish seriousness, interpreted</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C07_app240-f1831">her</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C07_app241-f1831">words literally,</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C07_app242-f1831">and</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C07_app243-f1831">looked upon Elizabeth as mine—mine</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C07_app244-f1831">to</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C07_app245-f1831">protect, love, and <pb xml:id="F1831_v_039" n="23"/>cherish. All praises bestowed</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C07_app246-f1831">on her,</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C07_app247-f1831">I received as</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C07_app248-f1831">made to</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C07_app249-f1831">a</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C07_app250-f1831">possession of my own. We called each other familiarly by the name of cousin. No word, no expression could body forth the kind</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C07_app251-f1831">of</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C07_app252-f1831">relation in which she stood to me—my more than sister, since till death she</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C07_app253-f1831">was</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C07_app254-f1831">to</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C07_app255-f1831">be mine only.</seg>
            <seg part="I" xml:id="C07_app257-f1831__I">
               </seg>
         </p>
         <seg part="F" xml:id="C07_app257-f1831__F">
            </seg>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
