<?xml version="1.1" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../FV_ODD/out/FV_ODD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="../FV_ODD/out/FV_ODD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Bridge Phase 6: f1831 chapter ii</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Frankenstein Variorum Project</authority>
            <date>2023—</date>
            <availability>
               <licence>Distributed under a Creative Commons
                                                  Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported
                                                  License</licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Produced from a corpus of collation output files for
                                                the Frankenstein Variorum digital edition on
                                                  2023-10-20T02:20:52.872461-04:00.</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <anchor type="semantic" subtype="end start" xml:id="f1831_chapter_ii"/>
         <seg part="I" xml:id="C08_app2-f1831__I">
            <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter1_div4_div1_p11">Every one loved Elizabeth. The passionate and almost reverential attachment with which all regarded her became, while I shared it, my pride and my delight. On the evening previous to her being brought to my home, my mother had said playfully,—“I have a pretty present for my Victor—to-morrow he shall have it.” And when, on the morrow, she presented Elizabeth to me as her promised gift, I, with childish seriousness, interpreted her words literally, and looked upon Elizabeth as mine—mine to protect, love, and <pb xml:id="F1831_v_039" n="23"/>cherish. All praises bestowed on her, I received as made to a possession of my own. We called each other familiarly by the name of cousin. No word, no expression could body forth the kind of relation in which she stood to me—my more than sister, since till death she was to be mine only.</p>
            <milestone unit="chapter" type="end" n="1"/>
            <milestone unit="chapter" type="start" n="2"/>
            <head>CHAPTER II.</head>
            <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter2_div4_div2_p1"> W<hi xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter2_div4_div2_p1_hi1">E</hi> were brought up together; there was not quite a year difference in our ages. I need not say that we were strangers to any species of disunion or dispute. Harmony was the soul of our companionship, and the diversity and contrast that subsisted in our characters drew us nearer together. Elizabeth was of a calmer and more concentrated disposition; but, with all my ardour, I was capable of a more intense application, and was more deeply smitten with the thirst for knowledge. She busied herself with following the aerial creations of the poets; and in the majestic and wondrous scenes which surrounded our Swiss home—the sublime shapes of the mountains; the changes of the seasons; tempest and calm; the silence of winter, and the life and turbulence of our Alpine summers,—she found ample scope for admiration and delight. tigating their While my companion contemplated with a serious and satisfied spirit the magnificent appearances of things, I delighted in inves causes. The world was to me a secret which I desired to divine. Curiosity, earnest research to learn the hidden laws of nature, gladness akin to rapture, as they were unfolded to me, are among the earliest sensations I can remember.</p>
         </seg>
         <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter2_div4_div2_p2">
            <seg part="F" xml:id="C08_app2-f1831__F">On the birth of a second son, my junior by seven years, my parents gave up entirely their wandering life, and fixed themselves in their native country. We possessed a house in Geneva, and a <hi xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter2_div4_div2_p2_hi1">campagne</hi> on Belrive, the eastern shore of the lake, at the distance of rather more than a league from the city. We resided principally in the latter, and <pb xml:id="F1831_v_040" n="24"/>the lives of my parents were passed in considerable seclusion. It was my temper to avoid a crowd, and to attach myself fervently to a few. I was indifferent, therefore, to my schoolfellows in general; but I united myself in the bonds of the closest friendship to one among them.
        </seg> 
    Henry  
         <seg xml:id="C08_app48-f1831">
        Clerval
        </seg> 
    was the son  
         <seg xml:id="C08_app50-f1831">
        of a merchant of Geneva.
        </seg> 
    He was a boy of singular talent and 
         <seg xml:id="C08_app52-f1831">
        fancy. He loved enterprise, hardship, and even danger, for its own sake. He was deeply read
        </seg> 
    in books of  
         <seg xml:id="C08_app57-f1831">
        chivalry and romance. He composed heroic songs, and began to write many a tale of enchantment and knightly adventure. He tried to make us act plays, and to enter into masquerades, in which the characters were drawn from the heroes of Roncesvalles, of the Round Table of King Arthur, and the chivalrous train who shed their blood to redeem the holy sepulchre from the hands of the infidels.
        </seg>
            <seg part="I" xml:id="C08_app58-f1831__I">
               </seg>
         </p>
         <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter2_div4_div2_p3">
            <seg part="F" xml:id="C08_app58-f1831__F">
               </seg>
            <seg xml:id="C08_app59-f1831">
        No human being could have passed a happier childhood than myself. My parents were possessed by the very spirit of kindness and indulgence. We felt that they were not the tyrants to rule our lot according to their caprice, but the agents and creators of all the many delights which we enjoyed. When I mingled with other families, I distinctly discerned how peculiarly fortunate my lot was, and gratitude assisted the developement of filial love.
        </seg>
            <seg part="I" xml:id="C08_app60-f1831__I">
               </seg>
         </p>
         <seg part="F" xml:id="C08_app60-f1831__F">
            </seg>
         <seg xml:id="C08_app61-f1831">
            <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter2_div4_div2_p4">My temper was sometimes violent, and my passions vehement; but by some law in my temperature they were turned, not towards childish pursuits, but to an eager desire to learn, and not to learn all things indiscriminately. I confess that neither the structure of languages, nor the code of governments, nor the politics of various states, possessed attractions for me. It was the secrets of heaven and earth that I desired to learn; and whether it was the outward substance of things, or the inner spirit of nature and the mysterious soul of man that occupied me, still my enquiries were directed to the metaphysical, or, in its highest sense, the physical secrets of the world.</p>
            <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter2_div4_div2_p5">Meanwhile Clerval occupied himself, so to speak, with the moral relations of things. The busy stage of life, the virtues of heroes, and the actions of men, were his theme; and his hope and his dream was to become one among those <pb xml:id="F1831_v_041" n="25"/>whose names are recorded in story, as the gallant and adventurous benefactors of our species. The saintly soul of Elizabeth shone like a shrine-dedicated lamp in our peaceful home. Her sympathy was ours; her smile, her soft voice, the sweet glance of her celestial eyes, were ever there to bless and animate us. She was the living spirit of love to soften and attract: I might have become sullen in my study, rough through the ardour of my nature, but that she was there to subdue me to a semblance of her own gentleness. And Clerval—could aught ill entrench on the noble spirit of Clerval?—yet he might not have been so perfectly humane, so thoughtful in his generosity—so full of kindness and tenderness amidst his passion for adventurous exploit, had she not unfolded to him the real loveliness of beneficence, and made the doing good the end and aim of his soaring ambition.</p>
         </seg>
         <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter2_div4_div2_p6">
            <seg xml:id="C08_app78-f1831">
        I feel
        </seg>
            <seg xml:id="C08_app79-f1831">
        exquisite pleasure in dwelling on the recollections of childhood, before misfortune had tainted my mind, and changed its bright visions of extensive usefulness into gloomy and narrow reflections upon self.
        </seg>
            <seg xml:id="C08_app80-f1831">
        Besides,
        </seg>
            <seg xml:id="C08_app81-f1831">
        in drawing the picture of my early days, I
        </seg>
            <seg xml:id="C08_app82-f1831">
        also
        </seg>
            <seg xml:id="C08_app83-f1831">
        record those events which led, by insensible
        </seg>
            <seg xml:id="C08_app84-f1831">
        steps,
        </seg>
            <seg part="I" xml:id="C08_app85-f1831__I">
        to my after tale of misery: for when I would account to myself for the birth of that passion, which afterwards ruled my destiny, I find it arise, like a mountain river, from ignoble and almost forgotten sources; but, swelling as it proceeded, it became the torrent which, in its course, has swept away all my hopes and joys. </seg>
         </p>
         <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter2_div4_div2_p7">
            <seg part="F" xml:id="C08_app85-f1831__F">
               </seg> 
    Natural philosophy 
         <seg xml:id="C08_app87-f1831">
        is the genius that has regulated my
        </seg>
            <seg xml:id="C08_app88-f1831">
        fate; I desire, therefore,
        </seg> 
    in this 
         <seg xml:id="C08_app90-f1831">
        narration,
        </seg> 
    to 
         <seg xml:id="C08_app92-f1831">
        state
        </seg> 
    those facts which led to my 
         <seg xml:id="C08_app94-f1831">
        predilection
        </seg> 
    for that science. When I was  
         <seg xml:id="C08_app97-f1831">
        thirteen
        </seg> 
    years 
         <seg xml:id="C08_app99-f1831">
        of age,
        </seg> 
    we all went on a party of pleasure to 
         <seg xml:id="C08_app101-f1831">
        the baths near Thonon: the
        </seg> 
    inclemency of the weather obliged us to remain a day confined to the inn. In this house I chanced to 
         <seg xml:id="C08_app103-f1831">
        find
        </seg> 
    a 
         <seg xml:id="C08_app105-f1831">
        volume
        </seg>
            <seg xml:id="C08_app106-f1831">
        of the works of Cornelius Agrippa.
        </seg>
            <seg xml:id="C08_app107-f1831">
        I opened it with
        </seg>
            <seg xml:id="C08_app108-f1831">
        apathy;
        </seg> 
    the theory 
         <seg xml:id="C08_app110-f1831">
        which
        </seg> 
    he 
         <seg xml:id="C08_app112-f1831">
        attempts
        </seg> 
    to 
         <seg xml:id="C08_app114-f1831">
        demonstrate,
        </seg> 
    and the wonderful facts 
         <seg xml:id="C08_app116-f1831">
        which
        </seg> 
    he 
         <seg xml:id="C08_app118-f1831">
        relates,
        </seg> 
    soon changed this feeling into 
         <seg xml:id="C08_app120-f1831">
        enthusiasm. A new light
        </seg>
            <seg xml:id="C08_app121-f1831">
        seemed to dawn
        </seg> 
    upon my 
         <seg xml:id="C08_app123-f1831">
        mind; and,
        </seg> 
    bounding with 
         <seg xml:id="C08_app125-f1831">
        joy,
        </seg> 
    I communicated my discovery to my father. 
         <seg xml:id="C08_app127-f1831">
               <pb xml:id="F1831_v_042" n="26"/>My father looked carelessly at the titlepage of my book,
        </seg>
            <seg xml:id="C08_app128-f1831">
        and
        </seg>
            <seg xml:id="C08_app129-f1831">
        said, “Ah!
        </seg> 
    Cornelius Agrippa! 
         <seg xml:id="C08_app131-f1831">
        My dear
        </seg>
            <seg xml:id="C08_app132-f1831">
        Victor,
        </seg> 
    do not waste your time upon 
         <seg xml:id="C08_app134-f1831">
        this;
        </seg> 
    it is sad 
         <seg part="I" xml:id="C08_app136-f1831__I">
        trash.” </seg>
         </p>
         <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter2_div4_div2_p8">
            <seg part="F" xml:id="C08_app136-f1831__F"> If,
        </seg> 
    instead of this 
         <seg xml:id="C08_app138-f1831">
        remark,
        </seg> 
    my father had taken the pains to 
         <seg xml:id="C08_app140-f1831">
        explain
        </seg> 
    to 
         <seg xml:id="C08_app142-f1831">
        me,
        </seg> 
    that the principles 
         <seg xml:id="C08_app144-f1831">
        of Agrippa
        </seg> 
    had been entirely 
         <seg xml:id="C08_app146-f1831">
        exploded,
        </seg> 
    and that 
         <seg xml:id="C08_app148-f1831">
        a modern
        </seg> 
    system of science had been  
         <seg xml:id="C08_app150-f1831">
        introduced,
        </seg> 
    which possessed much greater 
         <seg xml:id="C08_app152-f1831">
        powers
        </seg> 
    than the 
         <seg xml:id="C08_app154-f1831">
        ancient,
        </seg> 
    because the powers of the 
         <seg xml:id="C08_app156-f1831">
        latter
        </seg> 
    were 
         <seg xml:id="C08_app158-f1831">
        chimerical, while those of the
        </seg>
            <seg xml:id="C08_app159-f1831">
        former were
        </seg> 
    real and practical; under such 
         <seg xml:id="C08_app161-f1831">
        circumstances,
        </seg> 
    I should certainly have thrown Agrippa aside, 
         <seg xml:id="C08_app163-f1831">
        and
        </seg>
            <seg xml:id="C08_app164-f1831">
        have contented
        </seg> 
    my 
         <seg xml:id="C08_app166-f1831">
        imagination,
        </seg> 
    warmed as it 
         <seg xml:id="C08_app168-f1831">
        was, by returning with greater ardour to my former studies.
        </seg> 
    It is even 
         <seg xml:id="C08_app170-f1831">
        possible,
        </seg> 
    that the train of my ideas 
         <seg xml:id="C08_app172-f1831">
        would
        </seg> 
    never have 
         <seg xml:id="C08_app174-f1831">
        received the
        </seg> 
    fatal impulse 
         <seg xml:id="C08_app176-f1831">
        that
        </seg> 
    led 
         <seg xml:id="C08_app178-f1831">
        to my ruin.
        </seg> 
    But the cursory glance my father had taken of my volume by no means assured me that he was acquainted with  
         <seg xml:id="C08_app180-f1831">
        its
        </seg> 
    contents; and I continued to read with the  
         <seg xml:id="C08_app182-f1831">
        greatest
        </seg> 
    avidity. </p>
         <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter2_div4_div2_p9">
            <seg xml:id="C08_app184-f1831">
        When I returned home, my first care was to procure
        </seg>
            <seg xml:id="C08_app185-f1831">
        the
        </seg>
            <seg xml:id="C08_app186-f1831">
        whole
        </seg> 
    works of this 
         <seg xml:id="C08_app188-f1831">
        author,
        </seg> 
    and afterwards 
         <seg xml:id="C08_app190-f1831">
        of Paracelsus and Albertus Magnus. I read and studied the wild fancies of
        </seg>
            <seg xml:id="C08_app191-f1831">
        these writers
        </seg> 
    with 
         <seg xml:id="C08_app193-f1831">
        delight;
        </seg> 
    they appeared to me treasures known to few 
         <seg part="I" xml:id="C08_app195-f1831__I">
        beside myself. I have described myself as always having been embued with a fervent longing to penetrate the secrets of nature. In spite of the intense labour and wonderful discoveries of modern philosophers, I always came from my studies discontented and unsatisfied. Sir Isaac Newton is said to have avowed that he felt like a child picking up shells beside the great and unexplored ocean of truth. Those of his successors in each branch of natural philosophy with whom I was acquainted, appeared even to my boy’s apprehensions, as tyros engaged in the same pursuit.</seg>
         </p>
         <seg part="M" xml:id="C08_app195-f1831__M">
            <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter2_div4_div2_p10">The untaught peasant beheld the elements around him, and was acquainted with their practical uses. The most learned philosopher knew little more. He had partially unveiled the face of Nature, but her immortal lineaments were still a wonder and a mystery. He might dissect, anatomise, and give names; but, not to speak of a final cause, causes in their secondary and tertiary grades were <pb xml:id="F1831_v_043" n="27"/>utterly unknown to him. I had gazed upon the fortifications and impediments that seemed to keep human beings from entering the citadel of nature, and rashly and ignorantly I had repined.</p>
         </seg>
         <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter2_div4_div2_p11">
            <seg part="F" xml:id="C08_app195-f1831__F">But here were books, and here were men who had penetrated deeper and knew more. I took their word for all that they averred, and I became their disciple.
        </seg> 
    It may appear 
         <seg xml:id="C08_app210-f1831">
        strange that such
        </seg> 
    should arise in the eighteenth 
         <seg xml:id="C08_app215-f1831">
        century;
        </seg>
            <seg xml:id="C08_app216-f1831">
        but while I followed the routine of education in the schools of Geneva, I was, to a great degree, self taught with regard to my favourite studies. My father was not scientific, and I was left to struggle with a child’s blindness, added to a student’s thirst for knowledge. Under the guidance of my new preceptors,
        </seg> 
    I entered with the 
         <seg xml:id="C08_app224-f1831">
        greatest
        </seg> 
    diligence into the search of the  
         <seg xml:id="C08_app227-f1831">
        philosopher’s
        </seg> 
    stone and the 
         <seg xml:id="C08_app229-f1831">
        elixir
        </seg> 
    of 
         <seg xml:id="C08_app231-f1831">
        life;
        </seg> 
    but the latter 
         <seg xml:id="C08_app233-f1831">
        soon obtained my
        </seg>
            <seg xml:id="C08_app234-f1831">
        undivided attention.
        </seg> 
    Wealth was an inferior 
         <seg xml:id="C08_app236-f1831">
        object;
        </seg> 
    but what 
         <seg xml:id="C08_app238-f1831">
        glory
        </seg>
            <seg xml:id="C08_app239-f1831">
        would attend
        </seg> 
    the 
         <seg xml:id="C08_app241-f1831">
        discovery,
        </seg> 
    if I could 
         <seg xml:id="C08_app243-f1831">
        banish disease from the human
        </seg>
            <seg xml:id="C08_app244-f1831">
        frame,
        </seg> 
    and render man 
         <seg xml:id="C08_app246-f1831">
        invulnerable
        </seg> 
    to any  
         <seg xml:id="C08_app249-f1831">
        but
        </seg> 
    a violent  
         <seg xml:id="C08_app252-f1831">
        death!
        </seg>
         </p>
         <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter2_div4_div2_p12"> Nor were these my only 
        <seg xml:id="C08_app254-f1831">
        visions.
        </seg> 
    The raising of ghosts or devils 
         <seg xml:id="C08_app256-f1831">
        was a promise liberally accorded by
        </seg>
            <seg xml:id="C08_app257-f1831">
        my favourite
        </seg>
            <seg xml:id="C08_app258-f1831">
        authors,
        </seg> 
    the fulfilment of which I most eagerly sought; and if my incantations were always 
         <seg xml:id="C08_app260-f1831">
        unsuccessful, I
        </seg> 
    attributed 
         <seg xml:id="C08_app262-f1831">
        the failure
        </seg> 
    rather to my own inexperience  
         <seg xml:id="C08_app264-f1831">
        and mistake, than to a want of skill or fidelity
        </seg> 
    in my 
         <seg xml:id="C08_app266-f1831">
        instructors.
        </seg>
            <seg xml:id="C08_app267-f1831">
        And thus for a time I was occupied by exploded systems, mingling, like an unadept, a thousand contradictory theories, and floundering desperately in a very slough of multifarious knowledge, guided by an ardent imagination and childish reasoning, till an accident again changed the current of my ideas.
        </seg>
         </p>
         <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter2_div4_div2_p13">
            <seg xml:id="C08_app302-f1831">
        When I was about
        </seg>
            <seg xml:id="C08_app303-f1831">
        fifteen
        </seg> 
    years 
         <seg xml:id="C08_app305-f1831">
        old
        </seg> 
    we 
         <seg xml:id="C08_app307-f1831">
        had retired to
        </seg> 
    our house near 
         <seg xml:id="C08_app309-f1831">
        Belrive,
        </seg> 
    when we witnessed 
         <seg xml:id="C08_app311-f1831">
        a most violent and terrible thunder-storm.
        </seg> 
    It advanced from behind 
         <seg xml:id="C08_app313-f1831">
        the mountains of Jura;
        </seg> 
    and the thunder 
         <seg xml:id="C08_app315-f1831">
        burst at once
        </seg> 
    with  
         <seg xml:id="C08_app317-f1831">
        frightful
        </seg>
            <seg xml:id="C08_app318-f1831">
        loudness
        </seg> 
    from various quarters of the 
         <seg xml:id="C08_app320-f1831">
        heavens.
        </seg> 
    I 
         <seg xml:id="C08_app322-f1831">
        remained,
        </seg> 
    while 
         <seg xml:id="C08_app324-f1831">
        the storm
        </seg>
            <seg xml:id="C08_app325-f1831">
        lasted,
        </seg> 
    watching 
         <seg xml:id="C08_app327-f1831">
        its progress with curiosity and
        </seg>
            <seg xml:id="C08_app328-f1831">
        delight.
        </seg> 
    As I stood at the 
         <seg xml:id="C08_app330-f1831">
        door,
        </seg> 
    on a sudden I beheld  
         <seg xml:id="C08_app333-f1831">
        a stream of
        </seg> 
    fire issue from an old  
         <seg xml:id="C08_app335-f1831">
        and beautiful
        </seg>
            <seg xml:id="C08_app336-f1831">
        oak, which stood
        </seg> 
    about 
         <seg xml:id="C08_app338-f1831">
        twenty yards from our
        </seg>
            <seg xml:id="C08_app339-f1831">
               <pb xml:id="F1831_v_044" n="28"/>house;
        </seg> 
    and 
         <seg xml:id="C08_app341-f1831">
        so soon as
        </seg> 
    the  
         <seg xml:id="C08_app343-f1831">
        dazzling light
        </seg>
            <seg xml:id="C08_app344-f1831">
        vanished, the oak
        </seg>
            <seg xml:id="C08_app345-f1831">
        had
        </seg>
            <seg xml:id="C08_app346-f1831">
        disappeared,
        </seg> 
    and nothing remained but a  
         <seg xml:id="C08_app349-f1831">
        blasted
        </seg> 
    stump.  
         <seg xml:id="C08_app351-f1831">
        When we visited it the next
        </seg>
            <seg xml:id="C08_app352-f1831">
        morning,
        </seg> 
    we found the 
         <seg xml:id="C08_app354-f1831">
        tree shattered in a singular manner. It was not splintered by the shock, but entirely reduced to thin
        </seg>
            <seg xml:id="C08_app355-f1831">
        ribands
        </seg> 
    of wood. 
         <seg xml:id="C08_app357-f1831">
        I never
        </seg>
            <seg xml:id="C08_app358-f1831">
        beheld
        </seg>
            <seg xml:id="C08_app359-f1831">
        anything
        </seg> 
    so utterly destroyed. </p>
         <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter2_div4_div2_p14">
            <seg xml:id="C08_app436-f1831">
        Before this I was not unacquainted with the more obvious laws of electricity. On this occasion a man of great research in natural philosophy was with us, and, excited by this catastrophe, he entered on the explanation of a theory which he had formed on the subject of electricity and galvanism, which was at once new and astonishing to me. All that he said threw greatly into the shade Cornelius Agrippa, Albertus Magnus, and Paracelsus, the lords of my imagination; but by some fatality the overthrow of these men disinclined me to pursue my accustomed studies. It seemed to me as if nothing would or could ever be known. All that had so long engaged my attention suddenly grew despicable. By one of those caprices of the mind, which we are perhaps most subject to in early youth, I at once gave up my former occupations; set down natural history and all its progeny as a deformed and abortive creation; and entertained the greatest disdain for a would-be science, which could never even step within the threshold of real knowledge. In this mood of mind I betook myself to the mathematics, and the branches of study appertaining to that science, as being built upon secure foundations, and so worthy of my consideration.
        </seg>
            <seg part="I" xml:id="C08_app466-f1831__I">
               </seg>
         </p>
         <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter2_div4_div2_p15">
            <seg part="F" xml:id="C08_app466-f1831__F">
               </seg>
            <seg part="I" xml:id="C08_app467-f1831__I">
        Thus strangely are our souls constructed, and by such slight ligaments are we bound to prosperity or ruin. When I look back, it seems to me as if this almost miraculous change of inclination and will was the immediate suggestion of the guardian angel of my life— the last effort made by the spirit of preservation to avert the storm that was even then hanging in the stars, and ready to envelope me. Her victory was announced by an unusual tranquillity and gladness of soul, which followed the relinquishing of my ancient and latterly tormenting studies. It was thus that I was to be taught to associate evil with their prosecution, happiness with their disregard.</seg>
         </p>
         <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter2_div4_div2_p16">
            <seg part="F" xml:id="C08_app467-f1831__F">
               <pb xml:id="F1831_v_045" n="29"/>It was a strong effort of the spirit of good; but it was ineffectual. Destiny was too potent, and her immutable laws had decreed my utter and terrible destruction.
        </seg>
            <seg part="I" xml:id="C08_app484-f1831__I">
               </seg>
         </p>
         <seg part="F" xml:id="C08_app484-f1831__F">
            </seg>
         <seg xml:id="C08_app486-f1831">
            <milestone unit="chapter" type="end" n="2"/>
         </seg>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
