<?xml version="1.1" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
      xmlns:fv="https://frankensteinvariorum.github.io"
      xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Bridge Phase 6: f1831 chapter xxii</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Frankenstein Variorum Project</authority>
            <date>2023—</date>
            <availability>
               <licence>Distributed under a Creative Commons
                                                  Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported
                                                  License</licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Produced from a corpus of collation output files for
                                                the Frankenstein Variorum digital edition on
                                                  2023-07-19T00:04:49.4354614-04:00.</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <anchor type="semantic" subtype="start" xml:id="f1831_chapter_xxii"/>
         <seg xml:id="C28_app1-f1831">
            <anchor type="collate" xml:id="C28"/>
            <milestone unit="chapter" type="start" n="22"/>
         </seg>
         <pb xml:id="F1831_v_181" n="165"/>
         <seg xml:id="C28_app3-f1831">
            <head ana="start"/>CHAPTER XXII.<head ana="end"/>
         </seg>
         <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter22_div4_div22_p1">
            <seg part="I" xml:id="C28_app38-f1831__I">T<hi xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter22_div4_div22_p1_hi1">HE</hi> voyage came to an end. We landed, and proceeded to Paris. I soon found that I had overtaxed my strength, and that I must repose before I could continue my journey. My father’s care and attentions were indefatigable; but he did not know the origin of my sufferings, and sought erroneous methods to remedy the incurable ill. He wished me to seek amusement in society. I abhorred the face of man. Oh, not abhorred! they were my brethren, my fellow beings, and I felt attracted even to the most repulsive among them, as to creatures of an angelic nature and celestial mechanism. But I felt that I had no right to share their intercourse. I had unchained an enemy among them, whose joy it was to shed their blood, and to revel in their groans. How they would, each and all, abhor me, and hunt me from the world, did they know my unhallowed acts, and the crimes which had their source in me!</seg>
         </p>
         <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter22_div4_div22_p2">
            <seg part="F" xml:id="C28_app38-f1831__F">My father yielded at length to my desire to avoid society, and strove by various arguments to banish my despair.</seg> Sometimes he thought that I felt deeply the degradation of being obliged to answer a charge of  <seg xml:id="C28_app46-f1831">murder,</seg> and he endeavoured  <seg xml:id="C28_app48-f1831">to prove to me the futility of pride.</seg>
            <seg part="I" xml:id="C28_app49-f1831__I">
               </seg>
         </p>
         <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter22_div4_div22_p3">
            <seg part="F" xml:id="C28_app49-f1831__F"> “Alas!</seg> my  <seg xml:id="C28_app51-f1831">father,”</seg> said I,  <seg xml:id="C28_app53-f1831">“how</seg> little do you know  <seg xml:id="C28_app55-f1831">me.</seg> Human beings, their feelings and  <seg xml:id="C28_app57-f1831">passions,</seg> would indeed be  <seg xml:id="C28_app59-f1831">degraded</seg> if such a wretch as I felt pride.  <seg xml:id="C28_app61-f1831">Justine,</seg> poor unhappy  <seg xml:id="C28_app63-f1831">Justine,</seg> was as innocent as  <seg xml:id="C28_app65-f1831">I,</seg> and she suffered the same  <seg xml:id="C28_app67-f1831">charge;</seg> she died for  <seg xml:id="C28_app69-f1831">it;</seg> and I am the cause of  <seg xml:id="C28_app71-f1831">this—I</seg> murdered her.  <seg xml:id="C28_app73-f1831">William, Justine,</seg> and  <seg xml:id="C28_app75-f1831">Henry—they</seg> all died by my  <seg xml:id="C28_app77-f1831">hands.”</seg>
         </p>
         <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter22_div4_div22_p4"> My father had <seg xml:id="C28_app79-f1831">often,</seg> during my  <seg xml:id="C28_app81-f1831">imprisonment,</seg> heard me make the same  <seg xml:id="C28_app83-f1831">assertion;</seg> when  <seg xml:id="C28_app85-f1831">I</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C28_app86-f1831">thus</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C28_app87-f1831">accused</seg> myself, he sometimes seemed to  <seg xml:id="C28_app89-f1831">desire an explanation,</seg> and at others he appeared to consider it as  <seg xml:id="C28_app91-f1831">the offspring of</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C28_app92-f1831">delirium, and that,</seg> during my  <seg xml:id="C28_app94-f1831">illness,</seg> some idea of this kind had presented itself to my  <seg xml:id="C28_app96-f1831">imagination,</seg> the  <seg xml:id="C28_app98-f1831">remembrance</seg> of which I preserved in my  <seg xml:id="C28_app100-f1831">convalescence. I</seg> avoided  <seg xml:id="C28_app102-f1831">explanation, <pb xml:id="F1831_v_182" n="166"/>and</seg> maintained a continual silence concerning the wretch I had created. I had a  <seg xml:id="C28_app104-f1831">persuasion</seg> that I should be supposed  <seg xml:id="C28_app106-f1831">mad;</seg> and this  <seg xml:id="C28_app108-f1831">in itself would for ever</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C28_app109-f1831">have chained</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C28_app110-f1831">my tongue. But, besides, I could not bring myself to disclose a secret which would fill my hearer with consternation, and make fear and unnatural horror the inmates of his breast. I checked, therefore, my impatient thirst for sympathy, and was silent</seg> when I would have given  <seg xml:id="C28_app112-f1831">the world to have confided the fatal secret. Yet still words like those I have recorded, would burst uncontrollably from me. I could offer no explanation of them; but their truth in part relieved the burden of my mysterious woe.</seg>
            <seg part="I" xml:id="C28_app113-f1831__I">
               </seg>
         </p>
         <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter22_div4_div22_p5">
            <seg part="F" xml:id="C28_app113-f1831__F"> Upon this</seg> occasion  <seg xml:id="C28_app115-f1831">my father</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C28_app116-f1831">said,</seg> with an expression of unbounded  <seg xml:id="C28_app118-f1831">wonder, “My dearest Victor, what infatuation is this?</seg> My dear son, I entreat you  <seg xml:id="C28_app120-f1831">never</seg> to make  <seg xml:id="C28_app122-f1831">such</seg> an assertion  <seg xml:id="C28_app124-f1831">again.”</seg>
         </p>
         <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter22_div4_div22_p6">
            <seg xml:id="C28_app126-f1831">“I</seg> am not  <seg xml:id="C28_app128-f1831">mad,”</seg> I cried  <seg xml:id="C28_app130-f1831">energetically; “the</seg> sun and the  <seg xml:id="C28_app132-f1831">heavens,</seg> who have viewed my  <seg xml:id="C28_app134-f1831">operations,</seg> can bear witness of my truth. I  <seg xml:id="C28_app136-f1831">am</seg> the assassin of those most innocent  <seg xml:id="C28_app138-f1831">victims;</seg> they died by my machinations. A thousand times would I  <seg xml:id="C28_app140-f1831">have shed my own</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C28_app141-f1831">blood,</seg> drop  <seg xml:id="C28_app143-f1831">by</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C28_app144-f1831">drop,</seg> to have saved their  <seg xml:id="C28_app146-f1831">lives;</seg> but I could not, my father, indeed I could not sacrifice the whole human  <seg xml:id="C28_app148-f1831">race.”</seg>
            <seg part="I" xml:id="C28_app149-f1831__I">
               </seg>
         </p>
         <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter22_div4_div22_p7">
            <seg part="F" xml:id="C28_app149-f1831__F"> The conclusion of this speech</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C28_app150-f1831">convinced</seg> my father that my ideas were  <seg xml:id="C28_app152-f1831">deranged,</seg> and  <seg xml:id="C28_app154-f1831">he</seg> instantly  <seg xml:id="C28_app156-f1831">changed</seg> the subject of our  <seg xml:id="C28_app158-f1831">conversation, and</seg> endeavoured to alter the course of my thoughts. He wished as much as possible to obliterate the memory of the scenes  <seg xml:id="C28_app160-f1831">that had taken place</seg> in  <seg xml:id="C28_app162-f1831">Ireland,</seg> and never  <seg xml:id="C28_app164-f1831">alluded to</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C28_app165-f1831">them,</seg> or suffered me to speak of my misfortunes.  <seg part="I" xml:id="C28_app167-f1831__I">
               </seg>
         </p>
         <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter22_div4_div22_p8">
            <seg part="F" xml:id="C28_app167-f1831__F">
               </seg> As time passed away I became more  <seg xml:id="C28_app169-f1831">calm:</seg> misery had her dwelling in my  <seg xml:id="C28_app171-f1831">heart,</seg> but I no longer talked in the same incoherent manner   <seg xml:id="C28_app174-f1831">of my own crimes; sufficient for me was the consciousness of them. By the utmost</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C28_app175-f1831">self-violence,</seg> I curbed the imperious voice of  <seg xml:id="C28_app177-f1831">wretchedness,</seg> which  <seg xml:id="C28_app179-f1831">sometimes desired</seg> to declare itself to the whole  <seg xml:id="C28_app181-f1831">world;</seg> and my manners were calmer and more composed than they had ever been since my journey to  <seg xml:id="C28_app183-f1831">the sea of ice.</seg>
         </p>
         <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter22_div4_div22_p9">
            <seg xml:id="C28_app185-f1831">A few days before we left Paris on our way</seg> to  <seg xml:id="C28_app191-f1831">Switzerland,</seg> I received the following letter from  <seg part="I" xml:id="C28_app200-f1831__I">Elizabeth:— </seg>
         </p>
         <seg part="F" xml:id="C28_app200-f1831__F">
            </seg>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
